<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sub-poena from the star-chamber of heauen A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 4. of August. 1622. With some particular enlargements which the limited time would not then allow. By Dan. Donne, Master of Arts, and minister of the Word.</title>
            <author>Donne, Daniel, d. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856350</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1094:6b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sub-poena from the star-chamber of heauen A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 4. of August. 1622. With some particular enlargements which the limited time would not then allow. By Dan. Donne, Master of Arts, and minister of the Word.</title>
                  <author>Donne, Daniel, d. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathewes for Iohn Grismond, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Alley at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>With: Heauens ioy, for a sinners repentance / by Iohn Denison. London : Printed by G.P. for Iohn Budge ..., 1623.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:1"/>
            <p>A SVB-POENA FROM THE STAR-CHAMBER OF HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preached at Pauls Croſſe</hi> the 4. of Auguſt. 1622.</p>
            <p>With ſome particular Enlargements <hi>which the limited time would</hi> not then allow.</p>
            <p>By DAN. DONNE, Maſter of Arts, and <hi>Minister of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Auguſt. Confeſſ. lib. 8. cap. 12.</bibl> Tolle, Lege: Tolle, Lege.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Auguſtine Mathewes</hi> for <hi>John Griſmand,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley at the Signe of the Gunne. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:2"/>
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:177608:2"/>
               <hi>Honoratiſſ. Dominis.</hi> IOHANNI COM<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> DE HOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERNESSE, VICE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COM. HADDING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON, ET BARON DE KINGSTON AD THAMESIN, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>ET</hi> DOMINO HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICO HOBART, MIL. ET BARONET. CAPIT. IVST. DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NI REGIS DE BANCO.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NEC NON</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:3"/>
            <p>VIRO VERE <hi>RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERENDO</hi> MVLTIS QVE NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINIBVS COLENDO IOHANNI DONNE DOCTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RI IN SACRA THEOLOG. ET DECANO ECCLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIae DIVI PAVLI LONDON.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANIEL DONNE HAS SVAS QVALESCVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QVE MEDITATIONES HVMILLIME. D. D. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I haue in the Title-page of this Booke rendered a ſufficient reaſon of the Excreſcencie of this Sermon. Yet for thy more particular ſatisfaction, vnderſtand, that from the Beginning of it to the 52. Page, I preached it word for word, as it is Printed. Now becauſe many at the Croſſe had runne into Deſperate Debts, Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much Time of the Auditory, as they neuer meant to repay: therefore I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to content my ſelfe with a briefe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſticall Explication of the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that remained, and ſo, to keepe my ſelfe out of Deot: rather then Borrow what I thought I ſhould neuer r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. Since, being ſolicited to Publiſh what I then Preached: that each Part might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy its iuſt Proportion for the Exact Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177608:5"/> 
               <hi>of the whole, I haue enlarged my ſelfe in Thoſe laſt Particulars: and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Paines therein to thy Candid Interpretation. If thou meete with any Faults in the Print, they are I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe but Literall, and ſuch as will ſcarce puzzle the moſt Illiterate. Correct them, if thou pleaſe, with thy Pen. If there be any thing amiſſe either in the Method, or Matter: thy Friendly Information ſhall be Thrice acceptable. In the meane time, I aduiſe Thee to Read with vnderſtanding, to Remember what thou doeſt Read: And the Lord giue thee grace to practiſe what thou doeſt remember. Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt, DAN. DONNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="subpoena">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177608:5"/>
            <head>A SVBPOENA from the <hi>Star-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Heauen.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LVKE 3. 9.</bibl>
               <q>Now is the Axe layd vnto the root of the the trees: euery tree therefore not brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging foorth good fruit, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Text</hi> at the firſt bluſh, appeareth like it ſelfe, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a face of vtter <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſtruction:</hi> paralell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> Pſa. 137. 7. <hi>Downe with it, down with it, euen to the ground.</hi> It beginneth with the <hi>Axe,</hi> and endeth with <hi>Fire,</hi> two merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe inſtruments of <hi>ruine &amp; deſtruction.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> makes worke for the <hi>latter;</hi> the <hi>Axe</hi> for the <hi>Fire:</hi> for the <hi>Axe is laid</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177608:6"/> 
               <hi>vnto the root of the tree,</hi> that the <hi>tree</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>cut downe,</hi> may be <hi>caſt into the fire.</hi> The <hi>entrance</hi> into this <hi>Text</hi> doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reſemble <hi>that</hi> into <hi>Paradiſe: there</hi> was a <hi>flaming ſword,</hi> Gen. 3. 24. <hi>heere</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3. 24.</note> a <hi>fearefull Axe:</hi> yet <hi>both</hi> farre different for their ends: <hi>that</hi> was forcibly to driue <hi>Man backe from</hi> the way, but <hi>this</hi> is forcibly to <hi>driue man into</hi> the way vnto the <hi>Tree of life:</hi> that, whileſt hee ſeriouſly conſidereth his fearefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, how that his <hi>tranſgreſsions</hi> haue made him like a <hi>Tree,</hi> vnto the <hi>root</hi> whereof an <hi>Axe is laid to hewe it downe,</hi> that it may be <hi>caſt into the fire,</hi> he may preſently turne vnto <hi>God,</hi> and in due time <hi>bring foorth fruites meete for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> leſt <hi>hee</hi> alſo bee <hi>hewen downe</hi> by the <hi>Axe of Gods wrath,</hi> and ſo periſh for euer.</p>
            <p>This <hi>ſacred Writ</hi> may not vnfitly be tearm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a <hi>Subpoena,</hi> ſent from the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> of <hi>Heauen,</hi> the <hi>high Court of Almightie God,</hi> and ſerued by <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Gods especiall Bayliffe,</hi> vpon certaine <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> that came vnto his <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> wherein is giuen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to vnderſtand, that they muſt not, as formerly they had done,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177608:6"/> content themſelues with an <hi>outward forme</hi> of <hi>repentance,</hi> a ſeeming godly ſorrow for their ſinnes: but muſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the <hi>truth</hi> thereof in <hi>bringing foorth fruites worthy repentance,</hi> making their <hi>appearance</hi> out of hand before almighty God in <hi>all holineſſe</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of life <hi>vnder paine</hi> of both <hi>temporall</hi> and <hi>eternall deſtruction.</hi> Now this <hi>Subpoena</hi> is expreſſed by way of <hi>Parable,</hi> or <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor,</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> is reſembled vnto an <hi>Husbandman,</hi> or <hi>Gardiner</hi> trauerſing his <hi>ground,</hi> with an <hi>Axe</hi> in his <hi>hand,</hi> hauing this <hi>reſolution</hi> in his <hi>heart,</hi> not to ſuffer any <hi>Tree</hi> to grow in his <hi>Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> that doth not <hi>bring forth good fruit,</hi> but to cut it vp euen at the very <hi>root,</hi> and to make of it <hi>fewell</hi> for the <hi>fire.</hi> The whole <hi>World</hi> is <hi>Gods Orchard:</hi> the <hi>men</hi> in the world are the <hi>trees</hi> of this <hi>Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: that man which bringeth not foorth</hi> the <hi>good fruit of good liuing,</hi> the Lord will vtterly <hi>root</hi> vp out of the <hi>land</hi> of the <hi>liuing:</hi> for, <hi>Now is the Axe laid vnto the root of the trees; euery tree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not bringing forth good fruit, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the reſolution of this <hi>Writ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> may it pleaſe you to take <hi>three</hi> things into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177608:7"/> your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>parties</hi> whom it <hi>ſummons</hi> and concernes, expreſſed,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Indefinitely, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, trees.</item>
               <item>2. Vniuerſally, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, euery tree.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>thing required</hi> of <hi>euery tree,</hi> and that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to bring foorth good fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bring forth,</hi> there is a <hi>production.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. We muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bring forth fruit,</hi> there is a <hi>fructification.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. We muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bring forth good fruit,</hi> there is a <hi>qualification.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Penaltie,</hi> in caſe the <hi>parties</hi> proue <hi>delinquent,</hi> and that is ſet downe,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. as <hi>intended,</hi> in the firſt wordes, <hi>Now is the Axe laid vnto the root of the trees.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. as <hi>inflicted,</hi> in the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Euery tree therefore not bringing foorth good fruit, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the <hi>Penaltie,</hi> as <hi>intended,</hi> obſerue,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> for the performing of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an <hi>Axe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. the <hi>Application</hi> of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is <hi>laid to the trees.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. the <hi>Place</hi> or <hi>part</hi> vnto which it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177608:7"/> applyed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vnto the root of the trees.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="4">4. the <hi>Time</hi> of laying this Axe vnto the root of the trees, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>now, now is the axe laid vnto the root of the trees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>penaltie,</hi> as <hi>inflicted,</hi> we haue to obſerue,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Duplicitie</hi> of it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. an <hi>exciſion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is hewen downe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. an <hi>exuſtion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is caſt into the fire.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Certaintie</hi> of it, intimated in the tenſe, wherein it is expreſſed: It is not ſaid, The tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, <hi>ſhall be</hi> hewen downe, and caſt into the fire, but <hi>is</hi> hewen down, and caſt into the fire, it being as <hi>certaine</hi> as if it were <hi>already inflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Generalitie,</hi> or large extent of it, no tree ſhall ſcape, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tree not bringing forth good fruit, is hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>particulars</hi> obſeruable in this <hi>text;</hi> I haue here as ye ſee, <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in paruo,</hi> a little world of matter in a few words; <hi>Singula verba ſuam haben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bullinger in 3. Matth.</note> 
               <hi>epitaſin,</hi> each word hath his weight, and is not lightly to be paſſed ouer: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomething of euery thing, plainly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177608:8"/> of all: I pray God as profitably vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the <hi>Parties,</hi> whom this <note place="margin">The firſt generall Part.</note> 
               <hi>Writ</hi> doth <hi>ſummon</hi> and concerne; <hi>indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, trees:</hi> not <hi>naturall,</hi> but <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall;</hi> for by <hi>trees</hi> is meant <hi>men.</hi> And let not this Metaphore ſeeme ſtrange: for as he did that was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours <note place="margin">Mark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3. 24.</note> patient for the recouering of his eyeſight, ſo may wee ſee men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>like trees.</hi> It is the alluſion of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Heathen,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>planta in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> a <hi>tree turned vpſide downe:</hi> his <hi>head</hi> is the <hi>root,</hi> his <hi>body</hi> the <hi>trunke,</hi> his <hi>armes</hi> and <hi>legges</hi> the <hi>maine branches,</hi> his <hi>fingers</hi> and <hi>toes</hi> the <hi>leſſer bough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> his <hi>skinne</hi> the <hi>barke,</hi> his <hi>ſoule</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>whole.</hi> And in the ſacred Scripture, we find it a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar metaphor, to expreſſe <hi>Man</hi> by a <hi>tree: Either make the tree good, and his <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 33.</note> fruit good; or the tree corrupt, and his fruit corrupt: for the tree is knowen by the fruit.</hi> Where by <hi>tree</hi> is meant <hi>man;</hi> by <hi>fruit,</hi> his <hi>workes:</hi> both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> are by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tearmed <hi>trees,</hi> Rom. 11. <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> the <hi>Iew</hi> a <hi>good O liue tree,</hi> the <hi>Gentile</hi> a <hi>wild O liue tree,</hi> Not to multiply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, let <hi>one</hi> place ſpeake for <hi>all.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribing the ſtate of <note place="margin">Pſalm. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177608:8"/> the child of <hi>God,</hi> he ſhall be (ſaith hee) <hi>like a tree planted by the riuers of waters.</hi> Thus <hi>man</hi> is a <hi>tree, cuius radix, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: folium, cogtatio: flos<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſermo: fruct us, opus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ludolphus:</hi> his <hi>will</hi> is the <note place="margin">Devita Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>root,</hi> his <hi>thought</hi> the <hi>leafe,</hi> his <hi>ſpeech</hi> the <hi>flower,</hi> his <hi>worke</hi> the <hi>fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as of <hi>Trees,</hi> ſome are <hi>high</hi> and <hi>loftie,</hi> as the <hi>Cedars;</hi> ſome <hi>low,</hi> as the <hi>ſhrubs:</hi> ſo of <hi>Men,</hi> ſome are <hi>high</hi> and <hi>mightie,</hi> like the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and the <hi>Okes</hi> of <hi>Baſan, publike men,</hi> men of <hi>eminent place</hi> in <hi>Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> gouernment: ſome <hi>low</hi> like <hi>ſhrubs, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men,</hi> men of <hi>inferiour note</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> This <hi>Subpoena</hi> concerneth not onely ſome <hi>one tree particularly,</hi> a <hi>prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cedar,</hi> or <hi>petty ſhrub;</hi> but <hi>indefinitely, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, trees,</hi> that is, <hi>any trees:</hi> yea <hi>vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, euery tree:</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Genera ſingulorum, ſome</hi> Princes, <hi>ſome</hi> Prieſts, <hi>ſome</hi> People: but <hi>ſingula gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, all</hi> Princes, <hi>all</hi> Prieſts, <hi>all</hi> People. So that you cannot ſay vnto me, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> vnto our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> when hee <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 22.</note> told them that <hi>one</hi> of them ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him, <hi>Is it I?</hi> or, <hi>is it I?</hi> or as the <hi>high Prieſts</hi> to <hi>Iudas,</hi> Matt 27. 4. <hi>What is it to vs?</hi> For as our Prognoſticators
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177608:9"/> in the Frontiſpice, &amp; Title page of their Almana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks, that they are calculated for the Meridian of ſome particular Town, or Citie, but may ſerue generally for the whole Countrey: So may I ſay of this <hi>Subpoena,</hi> though it was <hi>particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſerued vpon the <hi>Iewes</hi> that came to be baptized of <hi>Iohn</hi> in the riuer of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan;</hi> yet it concerneth <hi>all,</hi> both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for whoſe ſinnes our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſhed forth the <hi>Iordan</hi> of his precious <hi>blood:</hi> And therfore <hi>God</hi> doth ſend mee, though the meaneſt of thoſe that miniſter and ſerue at his <hi>Altar,</hi> to ſerue this <hi>Subpoena</hi> vpon euery <hi>one</hi> here preſent: <hi>Clamo &amp; mihi ipſe,</hi> I except not my ſelfe: <hi>Non enim tam improbus ſum, vt curationes aeger obeam, ſed tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in eodem valetudinario jaceam de communi malo vobiſcum colloquor, remedia communico.</hi> As <hi>Seneca</hi> moſt ſweetly, and more particularly to his <hi>Lucilius,</hi> Ep. 27. Seeing therefore it is directed to <hi>euery one</hi> of vs, let <hi>euery one of vs</hi> in the feare of <hi>God,</hi> as we tender the good of our owne ſoules, hearken with <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>attention</hi> what <hi>God</hi> in this <hi>Writ</hi> requireth of vs; and the <hi>Lord</hi> of his <hi>mercy</hi> giue vs <hi>grace</hi> &amp; <hi>power</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177608:9"/>
            <p>That which God in this Writ requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">The ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part.</note> of vs, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to <hi>bring forth good fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bring forth,</hi> there is a <hi>Production.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bring foorth fruit,</hi> there is a <hi>fructification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bring forth good fruit,</hi> there is a <hi>qualification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt for the <hi>Production, Euery tree</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. A Production.</note> 
               <hi>muſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bring forth.</hi> This verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a word of <hi>action:</hi> and <hi>action:</hi> is the <hi>life</hi> of the world. The Celeſtiall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures haue their <hi>continuall motion,</hi> the Sublunary are eſtated in <hi>alteration</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Officioſum boc animal Deus creauit, &amp; natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis eſt ſibi exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiorum inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: otium vero in naturale. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enim inertia cunctis corporis membris, nulli autemvt anime: E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cum continuo ſit na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter mobilis ociari non pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aqu in loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Man</hi> the great worlds <hi>little ſumme,</hi> hath an <hi>actiue ſoule</hi> infuſed into an <hi>orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall body:</hi> nothing is more <hi>naturall</hi> vnto him then to be in <hi>action. Sloth</hi> is not more the <hi>bane</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> then of the <hi>Soule:</hi> for the <hi>Soule</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aquinas) being alwayes naturally mooueable, cannot endure to be out of action.</hi> A garment <hi>out of wearing,</hi> is ſubiect to the <hi>Meath:</hi> Iron <hi>not vſed,</hi> contracteth <hi>ruſt; ſtanding</hi> waters, <hi>corruption.</hi> The wheele that <hi>lyes ſtill,</hi> is a fit Loome for the Spider to worke in. <note n="*" place="margin">Otium pului<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Satanae.</note> When man is <hi>idle,</hi> out of action, the <hi>Deuill</hi> is ready at his elbow
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177608:10"/> to preſſe him for his <hi>Souldier.</hi> What is the reaſon that many doe ſo luſt after their <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> offer ſo much incenſe vnto <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſacrifice ſo often to her <hi>Shrine?</hi> Is it not becauſe they are <hi>Idle?</hi> For as our learned Poſtiller hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, <hi>Vnchaſte folly is for the moſt part</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doctor Boys.</note> 
               <hi>begot of an idle braine, and hatcht in a lazy body. Otia dant vitia.</hi> Men in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, learne to doe nothing but eui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l: yea, like <hi>ſoft wax,</hi> they are then capable of any impreſſion, fit to do the <hi>Deuil</hi> any ſeruice. Singularly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable therfore is that Diſcipline which <note place="margin">The Preachers Trauels.</note> is practiſed in <hi>Caſſan,</hi> a principall citie in <hi>Parthia:</hi> there <hi>no idle perſon</hi> is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to liue among them. Sure I am in <hi>Gods vineyard none</hi> muſt ſtand <hi>idle. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> euen in his <hi>innocency</hi> muſt <hi>dreſſe</hi> &amp; keepe the garden of <hi>Eden. Man is borne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gene. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to labour as the ſparkles that fly vpward,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> It is euery mans Calling to <note place="margin">Iob 5. 7.</note> worke, to <hi>eat his bread in the ſweat of his brows;</hi> but to be <hi>idle,</hi> neither <hi>Church</hi> nor <note place="margin">Gene. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Comonwealth</hi> affordeth any ſuch <hi>Calling.</hi> In both ſome <hi>labour,</hi> ſome <hi>looke ouer,</hi> but none muſt <hi>looke on,</hi> ſtanding like <hi>ciphers</hi> to make vp a number, or fil vp a roome: <hi>God</hi> will not allow ſuch <hi>dead trees</hi> any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177608:10"/> roome in his <hi>Orchard:</hi> none muſt bee dry and barren, but <hi>all bearing Trees, Euery tree muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> bring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All Trees</hi> muſt bee <hi>bearing Trees,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. A Fructifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> 
               <hi>Trees</hi> that <hi>bring foorth:</hi> but this is not all: there muſt be <hi>fructification</hi> as well as <hi>production. Euery Tree</hi> muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bring forth Fruit.</hi> Wee read that our Sauiour, going from his lodging in <note place="margin">Matth. 21. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Bethany</hi> vnto the Citty of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſaw a <hi>Figge tree</hi> in the way, went vnto it, and finding nothing thereon but <hi>Leaues,</hi> left it not as hee found it, but curſed it; ſo that it preſently <hi>withered</hi> away. My beloued, vnderſtand the Morall, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> knew well enough, it was not the time of the yeare for the <hi>Figge tree</hi> to <hi>bring forth fruit:</hi> no, <hi>Non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ludolph. de vita Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>ficus, ſed ſidem, non fructus arboris, ſed fructus operis quaeſiuit.</hi> He ſought not for <hi>Figges</hi> but for <hi>Faith,</hi> not for the <hi>fruit</hi> of the <hi>Tree,</hi> but for the <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>Workes.</hi> It is not with <hi>God</hi> as it is with <hi>Man:</hi> Though we will not ſuffer <hi>dead Trees</hi> to ſtand in our grounds, but will <hi>digge</hi> them vp by the <hi>rootes,</hi> and haue them carried foorth to the <hi>Fire;</hi> yet we will ſuffer many <hi>trees</hi> and <hi>plants</hi> to grow in our grounds, not becauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177608:11"/> they <hi>bring</hi> vs <hi>foorth</hi> any <hi>fruit,</hi> or are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe profitable vnto vs, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they adorne and beautifie the ground with their pleaſing varietie. But <hi>God,</hi> as hee will not ſuffer a <hi>dead ſtocke</hi> to cumber his Orchard; ſo hee cannot endure <hi>fruitles</hi> and <hi>vnprofitable Trees,</hi> ſuch as grow <hi>pro forma tantùm,</hi> onely for faſhions ſake, that are all for <hi>leaues</hi> and <hi>flowres,</hi> but nothing for <hi>fruit.</hi> It is not the carrying of a <hi>Bible</hi> vnder the arme, It is not the frequent repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto <hi>Gods Temple</hi> to heare his <hi>Word,</hi> that maketh a ſound and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Chriſtian in the ſight of <hi>God:</hi> for though <hi>Happy is that houſe, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alwayes that Congregation, wherein</hi> Martha <hi>complaineth of</hi> Mary: as ſaith <note place="margin">Falix domus &amp; beata ſemper congregatio vbi de <hi>Maria Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> conqueritur. Serm. de Vngi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Aſſumpt.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard:</hi> Though it be a <hi>ioyfull ſight</hi> and a <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> to the beholding eye, when men and women are ſo <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly affected</hi> as they can finde in their hearts to ſequeſter themſelues from their worldly cares to goe to <hi>Gods Church;</hi> yet who is ignorant that this may be done for <hi>halfe endes,</hi> and <hi>ſiniſter reſpects,</hi> to haue our <hi>braines ſwimming</hi> in <hi>knowledge,</hi> and our <hi>tongues tipt</hi> with the <hi>Scripture Dialect,</hi> that ſo wee may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177608:11"/> beget an <hi>opinion</hi> of our holineſſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the better worke out our more <hi>priuate ends.</hi> It is not therefore I ſay, ſufficient that we be <hi>frequent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> vnleſſe we be <hi>doers</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: It is not a formall <hi>conformitie,</hi> in paſſages of <hi>Pietie,</hi> it is not the turning vp of our eye vnto heauen, it is not a volubility of <hi>diſcourſe</hi> in caſes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie that will ſerue the turne, all this is but a meere <hi>flouriſh,</hi> but a bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foorth of <hi>leaues and flowres;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>God</hi> will haue <hi>euery Tree</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>bring foorth fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though nothing but <hi>Fruit,</hi> yet <note place="margin">3 The Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> not any <hi>fruit</hi> will ſerue his turne: it muſt not be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſed</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>bad,</hi> but <hi>good.</hi> Euery tree muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bring foorth <hi>good fruit,</hi> the fruits of <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>tification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is here tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated <hi>Bonum</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>pulchrum</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wee muſt bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t muſt be <hi>beautifull</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Men:</hi> and <hi>good</hi> in the ſight of <hi>God:</hi> our <hi>fruit</hi> muſt be <hi>beautifull</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the ſight of <hi>Men;</hi> for our <hi>liues</hi> muſt ſo <hi>ſhine</hi> before men, that they may <hi>ſee</hi> our <hi>good Works, and</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:177608:12"/> 
               <hi>glorifie our Father which is in heauen.</hi> Our <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>fruite</hi> muſt be alſo <hi>good</hi> in the ſight of <hi>God;</hi> for hee will not be put off with <hi>counterfeit pietie:</hi> with him it is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>double impietie:</hi> for ſo ſhall we find it in our reckonings at the <hi>laſt day. Both</hi> then muſt goe together: wee liue heere in the ſight of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and therefore muſt with Saint <hi>Paul, heerein exerciſe our ſelues, that wee may haue a good Conſcience voyd of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Actes 24. 16.</note> 
               <hi>toward God and toward man.</hi> Moſt true it is, <hi>Onely good fruit is euer beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> but <hi>that which is onely beautifull, is neuer good.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Phariſes</hi> had their <hi>fruits,</hi> ſuch as were <hi>beautifull,</hi> full of beautie vnto the eye, they had their <hi>Almes-deedes,</hi> their <hi>Prayers,</hi> their <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Faſtings,</hi> excellent workes, excellent <hi>fruites</hi> of <hi>Pietie,</hi> at the firſt bluſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all compare, not to bee para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld, they being preſented vnto the eye of the world in ſo abſolute and compleate a forme: But were they as they appeared to bee? Certainely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe: for our <hi>Sauiour</hi> making a narrow ſearch into the nature of them, found that they were nothing better then the <hi>fruit</hi> which <hi>Solinus</hi> reporteth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177608:12"/> to grow in <hi>Sodom,</hi> which is in ſhew like other <hi>fruit,</hi> but being touched there is a ſtrange diſcouery, <hi>Extimae cutis ambitio fuliginem fauillaceam cohibet,</hi> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rine or skinne is but a caſe that is full of <hi>filthy ſoyly embers,</hi> and <hi>ſtinking aſhes:</hi> So their outward <hi>pietie</hi> was but a caſe to couer their inward <hi>impiety;</hi> their <hi>fruits</hi> carried a faire gloſſe, ſeemed by their outſide to ſide with the beſt: but <hi>All is not gold that gliſters:</hi> within they were full of <hi>pride, vaine glory,</hi> and <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie:</hi> men did ſee what they did, and thereby happily did glorifie God; but what they did, was onely to be <hi>ſeene of men,</hi> and therein they did diſhonour <hi>God.</hi> Indeed ſuch <hi>fruits</hi> ordinarily go for currant with man, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth direction for his <hi>Judgement,</hi> as hee is informed by his <hi>outward ſenſes.</hi> But it is not ſo with <hi>God:</hi> his <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing Eye,</hi> piercing the moſt inward and ſecret parts, hee prizeth euery thing according to the <hi>inward worth,</hi> and <hi>iudgeth</hi> of the workes of <hi>pietie,</hi> as they proceede from the <hi>inward puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> ſo that hee will not bee ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>counterfeit fruites:</hi> Such Wares are not warrantable,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177608:13"/> not marchantable with <hi>God; hee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth trueth in the inward parts:</hi> he will <note place="margin">Pſalm. 51. 6.</note> haue <hi>euery tree,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to bring forth fruit,</hi> not onely <hi>outwardly beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull,</hi> but <hi>inwardly good</hi> and ſound.</p>
            <p>Euery <hi>man,</hi> as ye haue heard, is a <hi>tree,</hi> euery branch of a <hi>good tree bringeth forth good fruit,</hi> ſo muſt each part of man: our <hi>Hearts</hi> muſt be <hi>fruitfull,</hi> in <hi>ſanctified thoughts,</hi> and holy <hi>deſires:</hi> our <hi>tongues</hi> muſt bring forth <hi>gracious words,</hi> ſuch as may magnifie Gods holy name, and miniſter grace and comfort vnto others: our <hi>Hands</hi> muſt worke the things that are <hi>good</hi> in the ſight of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man:</hi> our <hi>Feete</hi> muſt <hi>walke</hi> in the <hi>wayes of peace:</hi> in a word, we muſt <hi>giue all our members ſeruants vnto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 6. 19.</note> 
               <hi>in holineſſe; Abounding in the fruits of the Spirit, in loue, peace, long ſuffering,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5. 22.</note> 
               <hi>gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and in euery good worke,</hi> that may make vs perfect men in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> For this were wee elected before the world: <hi>God the Father did chuſe vs in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt his Sonne before the foundations of the world, that wee ſhould bee holy,</hi> and <hi>without blame before him in loue.</hi> For this were we created into the world, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177608:13"/> all things were made to ſerue for the vſe of <hi>man,</hi> man was made to ſerue his <hi>Maker:</hi> For this end were we redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out of the world: For <hi>Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 74.</note> 
               <hi>vs from the hands of our enemies that we might ſerue him without feare, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of our life.</hi> For this purpoſe doth <hi>God</hi> ſanctifie vs in this world with his <hi>Holy Spirit: I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 36. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Statutes, and ye ſhall keepe my iudgements and doe them.</hi> And for this ſhall we bee glorified in the world to come: <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, take the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 34.</note> 
               <hi>of the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world, for I was an hungred, and yee gaue mee meate, &amp;c.</hi> Thus will God crowne the holy liues of his ſeruants with an eternall weight of glory: <hi>Such honour ſhall haue all his Saints,</hi> which are fruitful in <hi>good works:</hi> not that they doe by their fruits of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, <note place="margin">No man can merit heauen.</note> and workes of pietie, merit ſo glorious a remuneration: <hi>alas,</hi> what can we pleade for by way of <hi>merit</hi> at <hi>Gods</hi> hand? ſeeing <hi>when we haue done all that we can doe,</hi> yea, that wee are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to doe,</hi> which is more then wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177608:14"/> can doe, <hi>we are but vnprofitable ſeruants,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 17. 10.</note> ſaith our Sauiour. And what is the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> for <hi>vnprofitable ſeruants,</hi> which God will render vnto them at the laſt day? Why, this is their fearefull Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Caſt yee the vnprofitable ſeruant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>vtter darkeneſſe, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> No, my beloued. <hi>Eternall life</hi> is not of <hi>mans merit,</hi> but of the meere <hi>gift of God through Ieſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt our Lord:</hi> As a reuerend religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prelate of our Church hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <note place="margin">Doctor King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of London.</note> wee may read of a <hi>Mercy-ſeat</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but neuer heare of a <hi>Steole</hi> of <hi>Merit,</hi> but in the <hi>Chappell</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Indeed God doth in many places of his Scripture promiſe the kingdome of heauen to all that leade a religious and holy life; but this his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is not grounded vpon a <hi>foreſight</hi> of any <hi>merit</hi> in man, but proceedeth meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the <hi>free grace</hi> and <hi>bounty of God,</hi> who herein dealeth with vs, as a louing and bountifull father with his child, promiſing him ſome gift of great worth, for the performance of ſome ſmall piece of ſeruice, happily for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto him a legge, or the like: that ſo by his bountie hee may bring his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177608:14"/> childe on willingly to tender that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend reſpect, which otherwiſe of dutie he is bound to doe. <hi>Holineſſe</hi> of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>conuerſation</hi> is that which God <hi>ſtrictly commandeth</hi> and accordingly <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth</hi> from euery Chriſtian: It is (as you haue heard) the end of our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Creation, Redemption, Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to bring forth good fruit.</hi> If we ſearch the Bible from the beginning to the ending, we ſhall find this to be the very pith, the marrow, the maine ſubiect, and life thereof: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the great goodneſſe of God, what he might <hi>command</hi> and <hi>compell</hi> vs vnto, in the name of our <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> and <hi>maker,</hi> he doth (conſidering our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and infirmitie) <hi>intreat</hi> and <hi>wooe</hi> vs vnto, in the language of a <hi>louing</hi> and <hi>bountifull Father.</hi> As S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt <note place="margin">Serm. 3. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domini.</note> ſweetly, <hi>Nobis praemia repromittit, vt nobis obſequia debita ſeruitutis extorqueat,</hi> he doth make vnto vs a promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneration, to draw vs to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that ſeruice which in dutie we owe vnto him in the whole courſe of our life and conuerſation: <hi>Vt quos nolle ſeruire conspicit ſponte, ſuorum beneficio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum poſsit promiſsionibus inuitare,</hi> that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177608:15"/> whom he ſees will not freely ſerue him of his owne accord, he might louingly and friendly inuite, by promiſing a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>This doth God, to make it knowne <note place="margin">VVhy God doth promiſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard to good vvork<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> and manifeſt vnto the ſonnes of men, 1. how ſweet and pleaſing a ſauour the ſacrifice of our holy Obedience doth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſend vp into the noſtrils of the moſt High. 2. That none ſhall euer inherit <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ioyes of heauen, but ſuch as doe wholly endeuour and bend themſelues forward to <hi>bring forth good fruit</hi> here on earth; ſuch as labour for the inward ſanctitie, and lead a holy and religious courſe of life. And 3. that they ſhall be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as ſure to participate of this his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed bounty, as if by their deſerts and merits they were intereſted in it. And that the <hi>Sunne</hi> of Gods <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>bounty</hi> may yet more clearly and freely reflect its beames vpon the eyes of your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, I hold it not vnfitting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we proceed any further in a word or two to remooue out of the way the opinion of <hi>Mans merit,</hi> which like a thick miſt and darke cloud the enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt, haue caſt before it, to the great obſcuring and impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177608:15"/> of the glorious <hi>ſplendor</hi> thereof. It is a point, I take it, well worth the time, and may iuſtly plead for your Chriſtian attention. Sure I am, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much for the promoting of Gods <hi>glory,</hi> and the furthering of our owne <hi>Good:</hi> for when wee ſeriouſly conſider the inſufficiency of our owne works to ſaue vs, we may learne a poynt of true wiſedome, not to leane vpon the <hi>broken ſtaffe</hi> of our owne <hi>Merits,</hi> which will ſurely deceiue vs, but wholly to relye vpon the <hi>louing mercies</hi> of God, which are <hi>ſure,</hi> and will <hi>neuer faile</hi> vs. Thus Gods ſhall be all the glory, and ours all the good.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that many of our moderne <hi>Diuines</hi> haue not a little ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died this point, and left the fruits of their learned Labours vnto the broad eye of the world, that who ſo liſt may looke into them, and receiue ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the full; for nothing of ſubſtance can bee ſuper-added vnto that, which they haue already ſet forth: yet I think it not amiſſe, conſidering the <hi>preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,</hi> to borrow a little handfull out of the liberall harueſt of their labours, and preſent you with a taſte of their fruits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177608:16"/> dreſſed after my owne faſhion: I doubt not but it will be pleaſing vnto ſome, I hope and pray that it may be profitable vnto all. Happily I may herein ſeeme to ſome to make an <hi>impertinent digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my text; but who ſo well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the drift of the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall find, and conſequently beare me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I doe not beg my Theame, pick a quarrel with that which the text of it ſelfe will not ſeeme to affoord and offer. That which God in this <hi>Writ</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of vs, is the <hi>bringing forth of good fruit:</hi> this is the maine thing intended in this text, and preſſed <hi>vpon paine</hi> of Gods furious wrath, and fiery diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for euer, ſignified in being <hi>cut downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi> As if he had ſaid more fully, yet briefly and plainly thus: If ye <hi>bring forth good fruit,</hi> yee ſhall be <hi>ſaned:</hi> but if ye doe <hi>not bring forth good fruit,</hi> yee ſhall be <hi>damned.</hi> Now, the <hi>not bringing foorth of good fruite,</hi> being the <hi>meritorious cauſe</hi> of our <hi>Damnation,</hi> (as you ſhall heare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward) one would thinke on the contrary, that the <hi>bringing foorth of good fruit,</hi> is a <hi>meritorious cauſe</hi> of our <hi>Saluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177608:16"/>
            <p>That we cannot by way of <hi>Merit</hi> challenge ſo magnificent a <hi>remunerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as God out of his great goodneſſe doth binde himſelfe by promiſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre vpon the <hi>Sonnes of Men</hi> for their pious and godly conuerſation, may be plainely demonſtrated vnto you by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers particulars I will at this time contract my ſelfe in fiue. In euery <hi>Worke</hi> to make it <hi>meritorious</hi> there are <note place="margin">Our vvorkes nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritorious for fiue Reaſons.</note> 
               <hi>fiue things</hi> requiſite.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gratuitie.</item>
               <item>2. Vtilitie.</item>
               <item>3. Proprietie.</item>
               <item>4. Puritie.</item>
               <item>5. Paritie.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Worke</hi> which doth <hi>merit</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at Gods hand muſt of neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be <hi>opus Gratuitum,</hi> a <hi>free-will Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> a worke of <hi>Gratuitie,</hi> and in no wiſe due for any other cauſe or reſpect. Seeing then we owe of <hi>dutie</hi> vnto God whatſoeuer we are or haue; vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly whatſoeuer we doe, can <hi>merit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> at Gods hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There muſt be <hi>Vtilitie,</hi> that <hi>Good</hi> which we doe, to make it <hi>meritorious,</hi> muſt be <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>commodious</hi> vnto him, at whoſe hands wee <hi>merit</hi> any thing. But <hi>no action</hi> of ours of what ſtraine ſoeuer it be, can bring any <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177608:17"/> any <hi>commoditie</hi> vnto God: for as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Iob, May a man be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 22. 23.</note> 
               <hi>profitable vnto God as he that is wiſe may be profitable vnto himſelfe? Is it any thing to the Almightie that thou art righteous? or is it profitable to him that thou makeſt thy wayes vpright?</hi> His <hi>Interogation</hi> doth argue a <hi>ſtronge negatiue reſolution:</hi> as if he had ſaid in a word, <hi>No mans righteouſneſſe can bee any way profitable vnto God:</hi> and therefore we can <hi>merit nothing</hi> at Gods hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In that by which we <hi>merit</hi> any thing we muſt haue an <hi>abſolute propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie;</hi> it muſt be our owne. Now <hi>Good workes, Good fruits</hi> are not our <hi>own,</hi> they are <hi>Gods:</hi> wee cannot of our ſelues ſo much as <hi>Will,</hi> much leſſe <hi>worke</hi> that which is <hi>Good,</hi> for it is <hi>God that worketh in vs both the will and the deed:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note> we can <hi>merit</hi> nothing at his hand.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There muſt bee a <hi>Puritie,</hi> our <hi>workes</hi> muſt be performed according to that abſolute <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Puritie</hi> which God in his reuealed will requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of vs: they muſt bee vindicated and freed from all <hi>vncleanneſſe</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection,</hi> which no man ſo long as hee <hi>liueth in the fleſh</hi> can vndertake for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177608:17"/> 
               <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>choiſeſt fruit</hi> he bringeth forth: for euen our <hi>beſt actions,</hi> were they nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſcanned, in ſome thing or other <hi>Carnis putredinem ſapiunt,</hi> as <hi>Caluin</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, doe ſauour and reliſh of the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib, inſtit. de Juſtif. fidei, Cap. 10.</note> of the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> happely they haue leaned to ſome <hi>ſiniſter reſpect,</hi> or haue not beene performed with ſuch <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>alacrity</hi> as <hi>God</hi> requireth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To make our workes <hi>meritorious,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>Paritie,</hi> there muſt bee ſome <hi>proportion</hi> and <hi>equalitie</hi> betweene that <hi>Good</hi> we doe, and the <hi>reward</hi> wee receiue for it: Now what <hi>Parity,</hi> what <hi>Proportion</hi> betweene our <hi>workes</hi> which are but <hi>temporall</hi> and <hi>finite,</hi> and the <hi>reward</hi> which is <hi>eternall</hi> and <hi>infinite:</hi> The <hi>Naturall Phyloſopher,</hi> and any one that is not a <hi>mere naturall,</hi> will tell vs that <hi>Finiti ad Infinitum nulla eſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> there is <hi>no proportion</hi> betweene that which is <hi>finite</hi> and that which is <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</hi> Therefore our <hi>choiceſt</hi> fruits, our <hi>beſt</hi> workes being <hi>defectiue</hi> in <hi>euery one</hi> of theſe fiue particulars which ought <hi>neceſſarily</hi> to concurre for the making of them <hi>meritorious,</hi> it is ſtrange there ſhould liue in this <hi>great light</hi> of the Goſpell any that dare attempt ſuch a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177608:18"/> 
               <hi>worke</hi> of <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> as to ſtampe mans <hi>workes</hi> with the Character of <hi>Merit.</hi> Sure I am in the Word of God we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as finde the Word <hi>Merit</hi> Indeed <hi>God</hi> doth very frequently in the Sacred Scripture promiſe a <hi>reward</hi> to the godly, and hence they fondly collect that the godly doe <hi>merit</hi> by the holineſſe of their liues: as if between <hi>reward</hi> and <hi>merit</hi> there were a <hi>mutuall relation,</hi> that no reward is giuen but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a preſuppoſed merit. For anſwer whereunto, I may tell them, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour the Sadduces, That <hi>they erre not knowing the Scriptures:</hi> for as the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 19.</note> haue obſerued, that which by Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Reward,</hi> is <note place="margin">Math. 5 46. Luc 6 32.</note> by Saint <hi>Luke</hi> termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Grace, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour</hi> or <hi>thankes;</hi> to ſignifie vnto vs, that when God rewardeth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of men, the <hi>reward</hi> is not to be aſcribed to any worth or <hi>dignity</hi> in the <hi>Creature,</hi> but wholly to the <hi>benignitie</hi> of the <hi>Creator:</hi> not to any deſert or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in <hi>Man,</hi> but vnto the meere <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> of his <hi>Maker.</hi> For as Saint <hi>Paul 2 Epheſ.</hi> 8. 9. a place worth the <note place="margin">2 Epheſ. 8. 9.</note> noting, <hi>By Grace we are ſaued through Faith, and that not of our ſelues; it is the</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177608:18"/> 
               <hi>gift of God: not of workes, leſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe.</hi> The <hi>Caeſe</hi> being ſo <hi>cleare,</hi> we may be bold to affirme that moſt <hi>blaſphemous</hi> is the practiſe of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> who both in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>Preſſe</hi> ſo ſtiffely contend to enthronize the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, impure workes</hi> of ſinnefull man in the <hi>Chaire</hi> of <hi>Merit,</hi> in which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by right but the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> obedience of the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God can ſit. My beloued, I dare confidently affirme it for <hi>trueth,</hi> and you may boldly take it vpon that terme, that no Mortall by building him vp a <hi>Babel</hi> of his <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> can euer reach Heauen: Heauen being a <hi>tranſcendent,</hi> too high for the ſhort reach of humane merit. The <hi>fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt face</hi> hath ſome <hi>Mole</hi> or <hi>Freckle:</hi> the <hi>ſoundeſt Pomegranate,</hi> ſome <hi>rotten Kernell: Corruption</hi> is a great part of the <hi>beſt:</hi> yea the <hi>beſt</hi> euen from their conception are wholly <hi>ouer-runne</hi> with <hi>corruption,</hi> from which they can neuer be throughly purged till the ſoule and the body by death be parted and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder: by reaſon whereof euen our <hi>beſt actions</hi> are <hi>ſtained,</hi> our <hi>beſt fruits wee bring forth</hi> are <hi>foulely blemiſhed,</hi> and wil not endure the <hi>Iuſt eye</hi> of <hi>heauen</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177608:19"/> them as they are <hi>in themſelues:</hi> the ſerious conſideration of this made the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> thus pray vnto God: <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 143 2.</note> 
               <hi>no fleſh is righteous in thy ſight:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my beloued, inſtead of ſtanding like Proud <hi>Phariſes</hi> vpon the tiptoes of of our owne goodneſſe, let vs with the Penitent <hi>Publican</hi> truely humble our ſelues before the throne of his <hi>Sacred Maieſtie</hi> for our manifold tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which bring vs vnder the curſe of the <hi>Law:</hi> for the manifold ſinfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and blemiſhes euen in the <hi>beſt fruits</hi> that euer wee <hi>brought forth,</hi> for which we ſtand guiltie before him: Let vs reiect the <hi>menſtruous</hi> and <hi>rotten ragges</hi> of our owne <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Eſa. 64. 6.</note> relying vpon the louing mercies of our <hi>heauenly Father,</hi> which hee hath ſet forth vnto vs in his <hi>Sonne Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who himſelfe <hi>alone</hi> by his moſt perfect and all-ſufficient <hi>obedience</hi> hath <hi>merited</hi> our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the wrath to come, and purchaſed for vs a <hi>Kingdome that cannot be mooued.</hi> This hath he done for <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 28.</note> vs: but how? vnder condition of our <hi>new obedience;</hi> of <hi>putting off</hi> the <hi>olde Man,</hi> and <hi>putting on</hi> the <hi>new:</hi> of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177608:19"/> forſaking the <hi>crooked paths</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> and following the <hi>ſtraight way</hi> of <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi> So that being redeemed and bought with the price of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> wee muſt not thinke we may liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the luſts of our owne hearts and whatſoeuer ſeemeth good in our owne eyes, for this is nothng elſe but a <hi>trampling</hi> of the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnder our feet, a <hi>turning of the grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi> the onely way to make our ſelues vncapable of that ineſtimable bounty of our <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Redeemer:</hi> No, no; ſuch as are <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified</hi> by the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſauing portion in his bitter death and paſsion, are alſo <hi>ſanctified</hi> by his <hi>bleſſed Spirit</hi> vnto all holy obedience, <hi>to bring forth good fruite,</hi> the fruit of good liuing: This is the true <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>cogniſance</hi> of ſuch as are of the <hi>houſhold</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> For as the <hi>tree</hi> is knowne by the <hi>fruit:</hi> ſo is <hi>Faith</hi> made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <note place="margin">Iames 2. 18.</note> by the <hi>workes</hi> of righteouſneſſe. The <hi>bringing foorth of good fruite</hi> is <hi>via Regia,</hi> the Kings, yea euery Chriſtians <hi>high-way</hi> wherein he muſt walke, if he make any account to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto that <hi>Spirituall Caanaan,</hi> to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177608:20"/> be a <hi>free Denizon</hi> of the <hi>holy Ieruſalem,</hi> that city aboue, the mother of the elect. For as among the Antique Romanes, the two Temples of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> were ſo contriued, that none could haue acceſſe vnto the <hi>latter,</hi> vnleſſe hee did take the <hi>former</hi> in his way: So it is with vs, God in his eternall decree hath ſet downe this reſolution, which like the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> will admit of no alteration, that none ſhall obtaine the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> but ſuch as liue in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace:</hi> The <hi>penny</hi> is paid onely to ſuch as <hi>labour</hi> in Gods <note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vineyard.</hi> The Crowne of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> is laid vp only for thoſe that <hi>fight a good fight, and finiſh vp the courſe of their liues</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Hence that of the Prophet <hi>Dauid, Eſchew euill and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 27.</note> 
               <hi>doe good, and liue for euer.</hi> To draw vp all in a word, though we can neuer bee ſaued <hi>for bringing forth good fruit,</hi> yet we can neuer be ſaued <hi>without it,</hi> ſuch is the <hi>neceſsitie</hi> thereof: <hi>Sola fides juſtificat, ſed non ſolitaria.</hi> It is a common, a knowne poſition, <hi>Only faith</hi> doth iuſtifie vs, but <hi>not faith alone: onely faith</hi> doth iuſtifie, as the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> by which we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and lay hold on the <hi>Obedience of</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:177608:20"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the only <hi>meritorious</hi> cauſe of our <hi>ſaluation;</hi> but not <hi>faith alone,</hi> that is, a <hi>barren,</hi> a <hi>dead faith,</hi> a <hi>faith without fruits;</hi> for that is no <hi>ſauing,</hi> no <hi>juſtifying faith:</hi> and therefore <hi>euery tree muſt bring forth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Haeretici bodie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a carnis dederunt, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam <hi>Ba <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> tenuerunt,—nec ipſas Dei leges aut mada<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe ad ſalutem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria, ſola fide omnes ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ari.—Vt via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituale deſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rent, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem de peccatis &amp; virtutibus ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m venena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuis dogenatibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feceru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do vllam bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum veram iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am, aut ad ſalutem neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter omnia in Sola ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locando. <hi>Stapl.</hi> promptuar. <hi>Mot.</hi> in Domi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. Pentecoſtes.</note> 
               <hi>good fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Doctrine we <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Preſſe.</hi> See then by the way, the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent malignitie of our broad-mouth'd aduerſaries, the brats of <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> in traducing and branding our <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Miniſters</hi> for <hi>Solifidian Preachers,</hi> ſuch as in their Sermons are al for <hi>faith,</hi> and nothing for <hi>fruits.</hi> Thus like curſed <hi>Vipers</hi> they vent out the venom of their malice vpon vs, of purpoſe to bring our <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> into contempt with their <hi>hood-winkt Proſelites,</hi> and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee will not with them beyond <hi>truth,</hi> adde to the worth of good works, and detract from the <hi>ſole efficiencie</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>obedience.</hi> Maugre their viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent malice, this is our abundant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that beſides the teſtimony of our owne cleare <hi>conſciences,</hi> which are vnto vs as many <note n="*" place="margin">Conſcientia miſſe teſtes.</note> 
               <hi>millions</hi> of <hi>witneſſes:</hi> thoſe many learned and religious <hi>Treatiſes</hi> of our <hi>Churchmen,</hi> which haue vndergone the Preſſe, &amp; are at this preſent extant:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177608:21"/> that little world of <hi>Chriſtian people</hi> by our miniſtery fed to their euerlaſting happineſſe, thoſe many holy and bleſſed <hi>Angels</hi> alwayes preſent at our ſolemne ſacred Aſſemblies: and <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> who is <hi>all in all,</hi> and <hi>aboue all,</hi> will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to our <hi>white Innocence,</hi> and their <hi>blacke Impudence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh <hi>my beloued,</hi> I would to God all of vs, both Prieſts and people, could as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally wipe away this their foule and falſe aſperſion, by <hi>bringing forth of good fruit,</hi> as by our generall <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>profeſsing</hi> the <hi>neceſsity</hi> thereof. But alas, the neuer too much to be lamented mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, whilſt out of our zeaie to Gods glory, we labor to maintaine the <hi>ſacred prerogatiue</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>obedience,</hi> and labour to pull downe thoſe <hi>proud pillars</hi> of <hi>merit</hi> which our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> of their owne heads haue <hi>erected</hi> to the honour of mans <hi>worthleſſe works,</hi> and the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, we careleſly neglect, and ſcarce ſo much as once think vpon that which is Gods <hi>chiefeſt glory,</hi> and the <hi>life</hi> of our Chriſtian profeſsion, <hi>bringing forth good fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember I haue read this cenſure of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, <hi>Omnium bonorum</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:177608:21"/> 
               <hi>principum imagines in vno poſſe exculpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annulo,</hi> that the <hi>pourtratures</hi> of their <hi>good Princes</hi> might bee cut out within the compaſſe of a <hi>little ring.</hi> Oh <hi>my beloued,</hi> is it not as iuſtly to be feared, that the like may be as truly affirmed of vs? So ſmall is the number of thoſe in this our <hi>Sardis,</hi> which haue giuen vp their <note place="margin">Reuel. 3. 4.</note> names vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (if we may take the libertie to cenſure the <hi>tree by the fruit)</hi> that ſhould the Lord ſend forth a <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem 5. 1.</note> to make inquiſition for a <hi>man,</hi> that is, a <hi>good man,</hi> one that like <hi>Iob</hi> truly fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> God, and is <hi>fruitfull</hi> in all holineſſe, he would returne, if not with a <hi>non,</hi> yet with a <hi>vix eſt inuent us,</hi> ſcarce is ſuch a creature found. <hi>Good men</hi> being like <hi>little veines</hi> of <hi>gold</hi> in great and mightie <hi>mountaines</hi> of <hi>ground;</hi> or like the <hi>gleaning</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 7.</note> of the <hi>eares</hi> of <hi>corne</hi> after the <hi>harueſt</hi> is paſt, or the <hi>gathering</hi> of <hi>grapes</hi> the <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> being ended: they lie but ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and very thinne, <hi>one in a citie, two</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>in a tribe,</hi> wheras <hi>Romiſh Idolaters, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet Profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>impudent tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> ſuch as are not aſhamed to glory in vngodlineſſe, and proſtitute their deeds of darkneſſe vnto publike notice, are the greateſt part, yea, very neere the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177608:22"/> whole number of ſuch as are called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to ſpeake of that <hi>Antichriſtian Spawne</hi> and <hi>Popiſh frie,</hi> though not one of the leaſt and lighteſt burdens vnder which, as the labour of her wombe this our <hi>Land</hi> groaneth. Proceed we vnto the ſecond ſort; and who is there ſo blind or deafe that doth not behold or heare, how plentifully this our <hi>Sion</hi> is furniſhed, yea rather how lamentably be peſtered with a numerous brood of <hi>Apiſh profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Mocke-Chriſtians,</hi> as I may tearm them, ſuch as in <hi>outward appearance</hi> might ſeeme deſeruedly to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtred in the roll, and ranked in the number of true <hi>Nathaneels,</hi> but are <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 47.</note> indeed as ranke falſe and perfidious, as <hi>Ioab,</hi> or <hi>Judas</hi> They would ſeeme by the <note place="margin">An outſide ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> preciſeneſſe of their habit, and demure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of behauiour, to be truly <hi>mortified</hi> to the world. To giue them their <hi>due,</hi> which our <hi>Engliſh Prouerbe</hi> will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the <hi>Deuil</hi> himſelfe: they will <hi>reproue ſinne, refraine</hi> from <hi>ſwearing, celebrate</hi> the <hi>Saboth,</hi> yea many houres of the weeke dayes in <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> labouring if they <hi>like</hi> the <hi>Preacher</hi> to digeſt it in their memories by <hi>penning</hi> and mutuall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177608:22"/> 
               <hi>conference:</hi> in a word (oh the <hi>ſanctitie</hi> of the <hi>Deuill)</hi> they will pretend a great deale of faire and religious dealing, ſeeme to bee Gods <hi>white children:</hi> but (oh the <hi>Deuilliſhnes</hi> of theſe <hi>Saints)</hi> doth it not plainly appeare, that they are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better then <hi>Deuils</hi> transformed into <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Angels</hi> of light? fell and cruell <hi>Wolues</hi> couered and clothed in <hi>Sheep skins,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Religion</hi> to ſerue but for a <hi>Stalking horſe,</hi> wearing Chriſts <hi>Liuery</hi> for their owne <hi>conueniency,</hi> that ſo they may the more <hi>ſafely</hi> and <hi>vnſuspectedly</hi> compaſſe their <hi>ſecret vnſacred endes?</hi> hath not <hi>Time</hi> the <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> reuealed this for a <hi>truth,</hi> that there are none more <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt</hi> in their dealings, none more <hi>coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, deceitfull,</hi> full of <hi>pride, enuy, hatred, malice,</hi> and all <hi>vncharitableneſſe</hi> then they, though they take vpon them a more ſtrict profeſſion of Chriſt then ordinary?</p>
            <p>In a word, as the <hi>Trojans</hi> were neuer more damnified, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n when <hi>Aeneas</hi> did put on harneſſe like vnto theirs, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into the midſt of their troops like a member of their army: So the true <hi>Nathaneels</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea <hi>godlineſſe</hi> it ſelfe neuer receiued more <hi>diſgracefull</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:177608:23"/> 
               <hi>affronts,</hi> then haue bin and are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally moſt vnhappily occaſioned by the <hi>counterfeit pietie</hi> of theſe ſo common <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall profeſſors.</hi> As <hi>Iudas</hi> betrayed <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 49.</note> Chriſt into the hands of his enemies; ſo theſe haue and doe continually betray the holy calling of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> and the ſincere Profeſſors therof vnto the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tongues of lewd-liuing <hi>Libertines,</hi> and vngodly <hi>Atheiſtes;</hi> yea, of many framed of a more ſober, honeſt and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable temper, to be ſcourged &amp; laſhed with tearmes of <hi>diſgrace:</hi> for let a man out of a holy reuerence vnto the ſacred Maieſty of God, make conſcience of an <hi>Oath:</hi> let him out of a ſincere heart bee carefull to ſanctifie the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of the Lord in all holy and religious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: let him vow himſelfe to all <hi>ſobrietie</hi> and <hi>temperance,</hi> and be zealous for the Lord of Hoſts in reproouing vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. In a word, let him heartily deſire, and accordingly truely <hi>endeuour to keepe a good conſcience in all things both toward</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Actes 24. 16.</note> 
               <hi>God and man,</hi> not partaking in the ſinful courſes of theſe wicked times, but labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo far forth as in him lyeth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure of grace hee hath receiued, to liue within the limits and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177608:23"/> compaſſe of an holy profeſsion, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted but <hi>preciſeneſſe,</hi> he is ordinarily derided vnder the name of a <hi>Cathariſt</hi> or <hi>Puritan,</hi> and of the moſt hated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted as much, if not more, then a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous bloody <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or damnable <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt.</hi> Thus the ſeeming-Saints of our age, by their ouer-haſty running after Chriſt for ſiniſter reſpects, haue caſt the true <hi>Nathaneels</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> behind hand in their iuſt credit and eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 47.</note> the world meaſuring the <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>all</hi> profeſſors by the <hi>Laſt</hi> of theſe <hi>falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not onely doth <hi>counterfeit pietie,</hi> Hypocriſie thus flouriſh to the great contempt &amp; reproach of ſincere profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: but in the third place we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that all <hi>vngodlineſſe</hi> hath aduanced it ſelfe and <hi>taken heart. Iniquity</hi> hath put on a brow of braſſe, and <hi>Impiety</hi> like a <hi>ſhameleſſe ſtrumpet,</hi> attended by <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency,</hi> hath taken vp her ſtanding in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtreet, and corner of Court, City, and Countrey: <hi>Ambition, baſe flattery, perfidie, drunkenneſſe, couetouſneſſe, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie, pride, lechery, luxury, injuſtice, theft, murther, adultery, feareful ſwearing,</hi> and <hi>periury, contempt</hi> of the <hi>Manna</hi> and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177608:24"/> 
               <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Gods holy Word;</hi> and what ſeldom heard-of crimes in former ages, are not the <hi>familiar minions</hi> and <hi>darlings</hi> of theſe Times! It is a tedious taske, and would prooue but an irkeſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to trouble your eares with a particular enumeration of all the ſinnes that rooſt, yea raigne in this <hi>Land:</hi> for it may be truly ſaid of it, as the <hi>Poet</hi> in his <hi>Epigramme</hi> vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> concerning his <hi>Theater:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quic quid fama canit, donat arena tibi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Martial.</note>
            </q>
            <p>There is almoſt no ſinne ſo peculiar to any forraigne Countrey, which is not preſented to the life vpon the ſtage of this Land: and there is almoſt no perſon of what place or faſhion ſoeuer that doth not act his part in them more or leſſe. Thus <hi>vngodlineſſe</hi> is become an <hi>Epidemicall diſeaſe:</hi> like a <hi>Contagious leproſie</hi> it hath infected and runne ouer the whole <hi>Body</hi> of this <hi>Land;</hi> and no part more then this <hi>Citie:</hi> in ſo much that it may truely be ſaid of vs as the Prophet of the Iewes, <hi>We are a ſinnefull</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 1. 4. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Nation, a people laden with iniquitie: The whole head is ſicke, the whole heart is heauy, from the ſole of the foote to the crowne of the head there is nothing whole</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:177608:24"/> 
               <hi>therein but wounds, and ſwellings, and ſores full of corruption.</hi> And which doth <hi>conſummate</hi> our iniquitie, though wee are ſo <hi>deſperately ſicke</hi> of ſinne that wee lye euen at the <hi>doore</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> and there bee ſcarce ſo much as a threſh-hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and eternall deſtruction; yet who is there that with patience wil ſuffer the Preacher, Gods <hi>Deputy-Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> for the good of his ſoule, ſo much as to lay his <hi>finger</hi> vpon thoſe his can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred ſores of ſin, which ſuffered to run on their courſe, will <hi>vncurably corrupt,</hi> and <hi>irrecouerably caſt away</hi> the <hi>whole man</hi> both body and ſoule. <hi>Sinne,</hi> eſpecially that which ordinarily thruſteth it ſelfe into the ſeruice of any calling, and like the <hi>ſiluer Shrines</hi> of <hi>Diana,</hi> bringeth in <note place="margin">Acts 19. 24.</note> any <hi>emolument,</hi> or <hi>reuenew,</hi> muſt haue a <hi>Protection,</hi> muſt not bee touched. The corrupt courſes of thoſe which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to Courts of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> the ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe of <hi>Church-robbers,</hi> fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and vnconſcionable dealing in <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate commerce;</hi> theſe and the reſt of your <hi>boſome</hi> and beſt <hi>beloued ſinnes</hi> proue but <hi>vnplauſible,</hi> but <hi>harſh Themes</hi> for a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers inuectiue. Sure I am, wee may ſpeake it <hi>feelingly,</hi> wee are <hi>ſenſible</hi> of no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177608:25"/> leſſe: for deale we ingeniouſly &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in reprouing the corruptions of the time? do we lay open your beloued ſins vnto the life? our <hi>labours</hi> are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with <hi>laughter,</hi> and our <hi>fidelity</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited with a world of <hi>neglect</hi> and <hi>iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Are not theſe the <hi>fruits</hi> that call this our land their <hi>mother ſoyle?</hi> I would to God they did not: I dare preſume yee will all paſſe your words that I haue deliuered nothing but truth: and I may ſafely add, nothing to that which might haue beene deliuered for truth: for like thoſe whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent to ſpie out the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> I haue cut downe but <note place="margin">Numb. 13. 23.</note> a <hi>Branch,</hi> with a <hi>Cluſter</hi> of the <hi>Grapes</hi> that grow in this our <hi>Eſchol,</hi> and haue brought with mee but a <hi>Sample</hi> of that <hi>curſed fruit</hi> this land in great <hi>plenty</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth. O that we who haue ſo liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly participated of the ſuperabundant loue and bounty of God, ſhould thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue meaſure abound in iniquity. The time was (O that we had the grace ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conſider it) the <hi>time was,</hi> when we were <hi>without Chriſt,</hi> and were <hi>aliens</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 12, 13</note> from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and were <hi>Strangers</hi> from the Couenants of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and had no hope, and were
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177608:25"/> without God in the world: but <hi>now,</hi> through the <hi>Mercy</hi> of the <hi>Almightie,</hi> wee who were once a farre off, are made neere by the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that ſo we might be no more ſtrangers and Forraigners, but <hi>Citizens</hi> with the <hi>Saints,</hi> and of the <hi>Houſeholde of God.</hi> Againe, whereas <hi>other Nations</hi> doe ride <note place="margin">Iam tua resagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur paries cum proximus ardet.</note> euen vp vnto their <hi>horſebridles</hi> in <hi>blood,</hi> haue their <hi>Corne-fieldes</hi> depopulated, their <hi>Townes</hi> vnpeopled, their neereſt <hi>kindred,</hi> and deareſt <hi>acquaintance</hi> moſt cruelly butchered, and their <hi>whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> expoſed to the <hi>iniury</hi> of <hi>Armes. Wee</hi> through the great Goodneſſe of God, ſit euery man vnder his owne <hi>Vine</hi> in <hi>peace:</hi> The Lord of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie continue it long amongſt vs: whereas <hi>other Nations</hi> ſuffer the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the <hi>Word,</hi> or at leaſt haue it ſerued out vnto them mingled with the <hi>Cockle</hi> and <hi>Darnell</hi> of Popiſh <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>traditions: Wee,</hi> God be thanked, haue the <hi>Word</hi> moſt <hi>plentifully</hi> and <hi>purely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> among vs; yea ſuch plenty of the word we enioy, that like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> we are <hi>crop ſicke,</hi> and loth that heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> which our forefathers in the time of Popery &amp; perſecution ſo much
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177608:26"/> longed after. I pray God this bring not a ſcarcitie of <hi>ſpirituall Bread</hi> amongſt vs. Whereas <hi>others</hi> haue been ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the ordinary ſuſtenance of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and waſted with miſery, <hi>hanging</hi> vp their <hi>harps</hi> vpon the <hi>trees,</hi> and <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating</hi> the <hi>ſorrowes</hi> of their ſoules into <hi>mournefull ditties,</hi> and ſo ending their miſerable liues: <hi>Our Garners</hi> on the <note place="margin">Pſal. 144. 13, 14.</note> contrary, haue beene <hi>full</hi> and <hi>plenteous</hi> with <hi>all manner</hi> of ſtore: <hi>Our ſheepe</hi> haue brought forth <hi>thouſands, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in our ſtreetes: our oxen haue beene ſtrong to labour,</hi> we haue <hi>no</hi> leading into <hi>captiuitie, no complaining</hi> in our ſtreets. In a word, no <hi>Nation</hi> vnder the Sunne can preſcribe and plead a greater por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>immenſe Treaſury</hi> of Gods mercy and fauours, then <hi>ours:</hi> the leaſt of all which ſhould for euer bind eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one by way of thankfulneſſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate himſelfe both ſoule and body vnto the ſeruice of his ſo benigne and bountifull a God, in all holy obedience, and newneſſe of life, to <hi>bring forth good fruits,</hi> the fruits of <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> But alas, we are ſo farre from bringing forth this <hi>good fruit,</hi> that on the contrary, we are <hi>barren</hi> in all <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:177608:26"/> and onely <hi>fruitfull</hi> in the <hi>damnable workes</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> ſucking in ſinne, as <hi>fiſhes</hi> doe <hi>water;</hi> like ſwift <hi>Dromedaries,</hi> running with full ſpeed into all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, <note place="margin">Prou. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> making it a <hi>paſtime to do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as once dreaming of that dreadful day of account, that great and terrible Aſsiſes of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee will execute his wrath and <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> vpon the children of <hi>diſobedience.</hi> O my beloued, let vs take heed we bee not deceiued. <hi>This is the will of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>euen your ſanctification:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 3.</note> now the wil and pleaſure of God is not barely propounded vnto man as a thing <hi>arbitrary,</hi> or of no great conſequence, whether performed or not: for as with <hi>bountifull promiſes,</hi> ſo with <hi>feareful penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> it is in ſacred Scripture frequently preſſed, the Lord as he hath a <hi>Gerizim,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 11. 29.</note> for <hi>bleſsing,</hi> ſo he hath an <hi>Eball</hi> for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. As he will moſt graciouſly and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally recompenſe all ſuch as worke <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> with an <hi>immarceſsible crown</hi> of <hi>glory:</hi> ſo he will moſt ſeuerely and terribly reward all workers of <hi>iniquity</hi> with an <hi>vnmercifull weight</hi> of <hi>miſery.</hi> They which like <hi>good trees bring foorth good fruit</hi> in due ſeaſon, <hi>their leafe ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:177608:27"/> 
               <hi>not wither,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>they ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 2.</note> 
               <hi>flouriſh for euer:</hi> But they which, doe <hi>not bring foorth good fruit,</hi> ſhall be like the <hi>chaffe</hi> which the wind ſcattereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the face of the earth, they ſhall periſh for euer: ſo ſaith the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> here in my text, <hi>Euery tree not bringing foorth good fruit, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire,</hi> which is the <hi>third generall Part</hi> obſerueable in this <hi>ſacred Writ,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The third gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall part.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>penaltie</hi> attending delinquents, ſuch as performe not what God in this <hi>Writ</hi> requireth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Penaltie</hi> is heere expreſſed, 1. as <note place="margin">God premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth before he punisheth.</note> 
               <hi>intended. Now is the Axe layd vnto the roote of the trees,</hi> 2. As <hi>inflicted, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tree not bringing foorth good fruite, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi> A <hi>Mercifull Method,</hi> and well beſeeming the God of <hi>Method,</hi> who is full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: though our ſinnes be ſo numerous and haynous, that like vnto that of <hi>Cains,</hi> they doe euen call and crie vnto <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4. 10.</note> God for <hi>preſent vengeance:</hi> though our iniquities be ſo enormous, and growne to ſo great a height, that they reach vp vnto Heauen, and euen pull God out of his <hi>Mercy-Seate,</hi> to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iudgement with vs, to emptie out
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177608:27"/> the <hi>full Vialls of his wrath</hi> vpon vs to our preſent fearefull confuſion: yet, Oh the goodneſſe of God, hee dealeth not with vs ſinnefull miſcreants accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our deſerts, and as many a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe <hi>Creditor</hi> with his <hi>Debitor,</hi> who couertly without the leaſt noiſe procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth an <hi>Execution</hi> againſt him, and <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> it vpon him, happily to his irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable vndoing, not ſo much as once fore-acquainting him with his <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that ſo he might in time thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome honeſt courſe for preuention.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>my beloued,</hi> though mans wayes are full of <hi>cruelty,</hi> yet <hi>Gods</hi> wayes are full of <hi>mercy:</hi> Hee would haue all the world to know, that he is not <hi>delighted in the death of a ſinner, but had rather hee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek 13. 23.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould turne from his wickedneſſe,</hi> &amp; bring forth fruit worthy of repentance, and ſo liue for euer: and therefore, as <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> ſhot three arrowes to forewarne <hi>Dauid</hi> of <hi>Sauls</hi> diſpleaſure, that hee <note place="margin">1. Sam. 20.</note> might the better prouide for his ſaftie: ſo almightie God firſt in mercy <hi>proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi> his wrath &amp; indignation, before in <hi>Iuſtice</hi> he proceed to <hi>Execution.</hi> Firſt, he is pleaſed to <hi>foretell</hi> vs that for our tranſgreſsions, for our not bringing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177608:28"/> forth good fruit he intendeth a ſeuere <hi>penaltie</hi> againſt vs, before ſuch time as he ſuffer it to be <hi>inflicted</hi> vpon vs: that <note place="margin">Praemoniti. Praemuniti.</note> ſo we being <hi>forewarned</hi> of that feareful euill which from God is like to befall vs for our falling away from God, we might in time <hi>make our peace</hi> with him, &amp; ſo <hi>preuent</hi> the <hi>execution</hi> of his wrath. For the more effectuall performance whereof, that wee may the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſpeedily addreſſe our ſelues, proceed we according to our propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>method,</hi> to take ſome punctuall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the <hi>fearefulneſſe</hi> of his <hi>fury</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied in the particulars of the <hi>penalty. Now is the Axe laid vnto the root of the trees: Euery tree therefore not bringing forth good fruit, is hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Each word</hi> (as you haue heard) bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a <hi>part</hi> and euery part doth moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently demonſtrate the Greatneſſe of Gods wrath and indignation againſt vs, and is of power to imprint <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> of <hi>terror</hi> in our <hi>hearts,</hi> were they as hard as <hi>rockes</hi> of <hi>Adamant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To take vp the words as they lye in their order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> behold the Lord of Hoſts is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177608:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>already</hi> vp in armes, and his wrath, like <hi>Iehu</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Nimſhi</hi> after <hi>Iehoram</hi> marcheth moſt furiouſly after vs: yea <note place="margin">2 King. 9. 10.</note> to our greater terror it hath <hi>already</hi> wrought it ſelfe within diſtance; for <hi>Now,</hi> euen <hi>Now</hi> is the <hi>axe</hi> laid vnto the root of the trees. <hi>Secondly,</hi> conſider we the <hi>inſtrument</hi> apprehended for the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution</hi> of his wrath, it is not <hi>Culter Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarius,</hi> a pruning knife, but <hi>Securis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Muſculus in locum.</note> 
               <hi>exciſionis,</hi> a ruining Axe. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> this ruining <hi>Axe</hi> is not <hi>vibrata,</hi> brandiſhed <note place="margin">Gorthan in locum.</note> or ſhaken ouer the trees, but <hi>poſita,</hi> it is put, laid cloſe to the trees. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> this ruining Axe is not laid <hi>ad truncum aut ramos,</hi> to the bodie or boughes of <note place="margin">Bullinger.</note> the trees, but <hi>ad radicem,</hi> to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, the root, which once hurt or cut, <hi>de tota arbore actum eſt,</hi> the whole tree doth periſh, and is paſt all hope of ſhooting forth againe. Such is the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie</hi> here <hi>intended,</hi> and is pronounced, as <hi>inflicted. Euery tree not bringing forth good fruit, is hewen downe,</hi> and to make it more fearefull, is <hi>caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a cuſtome among the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans</hi> that their <hi>Conſuls</hi> had as Enſignes of their authoritie bundles of <hi>rods,</hi> and an <hi>Axe</hi> carried before them:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177608:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Iuſtice to <hi>cut them off</hi> in caſe they proued incorrigible, and would not bee reformed with any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable correction. In like manner Almighty God hath his <hi>Pruning knife,</hi> and his <hi>Axe:</hi> Hauing planted his Ground with <hi>Trees,</hi> and not finding them <hi>fruitfull</hi> according to his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, like an expert and carefull Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with his <hi>pruning knife</hi> hee ſhreddeth and pareth off the <hi>luxuriant branches,</hi> and vſeth all ſuch meanes for their <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> as in his heauenly wiſdome he apprehendeth moſt <hi>prevalent</hi> and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall. Thus for many a yeare with <note place="margin">Quamdiu Ipes eſt remedii, ſtercoratione aut putatione ſubuenitur ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum vitiis: caeterum vltimae desperatio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium eſt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Secu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouetur ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di i. <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </note> much patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce expecting their improue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at length the ſeaſon of <hi>fructify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> being come, wherein hee reſolued to put a period to his patient expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he walketh towards his <hi>Plantation</hi> with an <hi>Axe</hi> in his hand, reſolued if after his ſo great care and coſt he finde any <hi>Trees</hi> that doe <hi>not bring forth good fruit,</hi> to <hi>cut</hi> them vp by the <hi>roots</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> them by for the <hi>Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word or two, to adde a little more light vnto the darkeneſſe of the letter. This <hi>Axe laid vnto the root of the Trees</hi> doth ſignifie nothing elſe but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177608:29"/> the <hi>vengeance</hi> of God which hangeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heads ready to fall ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Neſp vero n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ſecurim &amp; glad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pro grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dei vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta. <hi>Idem ibid.</hi>
               </note> vpon vs to our fearefull confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>My beloued,</hi> doth not the <hi>cloudy</hi> and <hi>heauy countenance</hi> of theſe Times promiſe and preſage as much? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take we a <hi>true Inuentory</hi> of our <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Apoſtacie</hi> from all godlines and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, we cannot looke for <hi>leſſe.</hi> I but the <hi>Lord is mercifull and Gracious, ſlow to anger and abundant in Goodneſſe and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34. 6.</note> 
               <hi>truth, reſeruing mercy for thouſands.</hi> True my <hi>beloued,</hi> and haue we found him <hi>leſſe?</hi> Doe not all thoſe gentle and more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable courſes he hath taken for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming vs from our ſinnefull courſes ſpeake as much? May not the Lord iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoſtulate and reaſon the caſe with vs, as he did with his <hi>beloued <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſai 5.</note> He hath <hi>Planted</hi> vs in a moſt <hi>pleaſant</hi> &amp; <hi>fruitfull ſoyle:</hi> he <hi>hath encircled</hi> &amp; hedged vs round about with his <hi>louing mercies:</hi> &amp; what could he haue added more vnto that which he hath already done? <hi>How oft, how long</hi> hath he labored for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion by the preaching of his Word: <hi>Sermon</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Sermon,</hi> with extraordinary earneſtnes and importunity <hi>knocking</hi> at the <hi>doores</hi> of our <hi>harts,</hi> that hearing him
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177608:30"/> 
               <hi>we</hi> might open vnto <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> enter in vnto <hi>vs: He</hi> I ſay, who onely is able to <note place="margin">Pſalm. 51. 10.</note> 
               <hi>create in vs cleane hearts,</hi> and make vs <hi>fruitfull</hi> in all holineſſe. And to make his Word the more <hi>powerfull</hi> for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, how often hath he <hi>actuated</hi> it by many temporall <hi>afflictions,</hi> which hee hath inflicted vpon vs: as <hi>inundations</hi> of <hi>waters, dearth</hi> of <hi>corne, loſſe</hi> of our <hi>fortunes, loſſe</hi> of our faithfull <hi>friends,</hi> and ſuch as had deepeſt intereſt in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: ſometimes ſcourging vs with the refractarineſſe and diſobedience of thoſe which through naturall or ciuill reference are neereſt and deareſt vnto vs: ſometimes making theſe <hi>houſes</hi> of <hi>clay</hi> (our mortall bodies) <hi>Hospitals</hi> for peſtilentiall and painful diſeaſes: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring the high-priz'd treaſure of our reputation to be rifled by wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Shimeyes.</hi> But alas, what hath all this <hi>pruning</hi> preuailed? What good work haue theſe and the like afflictions wrought vpon vs! Happily for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they haue a little humbled vs, and wrung out of vs a <hi>repentant teare,</hi> with a proteſtation of new obedience, of <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth better fruit</hi> for the time to come then formerly, we had done: but this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177608:30"/> 
               <hi>repentance</hi> of ours hath been as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh; but as a <hi>Morning cloud,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ 6. 4.</note> and as <hi>the morning dew it hath gone away;</hi> like <hi>Dogges we haue quickely returned to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 2. 22.</note> 
               <hi>our owne vomit,</hi> and inſtead of bringing forth <hi>Vuas,</hi> grapes, wee haue brought <note place="margin">Eſay 5. 4.</note> forth <hi>Labrucas,</hi> wild grapes: our <hi>grapes</hi> are <hi>grapes of gall,</hi> our <hi>cluſters</hi> be <hi>bitter,</hi> our <hi>wine is poyſon of dragons,</hi> and the <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 32, 33.</note> 
               <hi>gall of Aspes.</hi> My beloued, will God, thinke we, ſuffer himſelfe to be thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded from time to time? Are we ſure he will alwayes looke vpon vs with a fauourable aſpect, and neuer <hi>ſhut vp his louing kindneſſe in diſpleaſure?</hi> O let vs beware of <hi>carnall ſecuritie:</hi> it is as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and fearfull an euill, as the ſoule imbarqued in the body can meet with, whilſt ſayling in the Sea of this world. Certainly, if his ſo many gentle and mercifull viſitations will not reclaime vs from our diſſolute courſes, but wee will ſtil frequent our old ſinfull haunts, <hi>drawing iniquitie with cartropes, and ſinne with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cords of vanity,</hi> he will lay aſide all lenitie, &amp; deale with vs more rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſa patientia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>or.</note> and ſeuerely. It is not a <hi>pruning-knife,</hi> ſome fauourable affliction, ſome father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correction ſhall ſerue the turne: for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177608:31"/> (behold) hee hath put an <hi>axe</hi> into the hand of the deſtroying Angel, not like <hi>Abimelech,</hi> to cut downe ſome boughes <note place="margin">Iudg. 43.</note> from the trees: no, he hath giuen him a ſtraight charge, a ſtrict commiſsion, if he find <hi>any tree,</hi> any man <hi>that bringeth not forth good fruit,</hi> to <hi>hew</hi> him <hi>down</hi> euen at the very <hi>root:</hi> that is, by death to root him out of the land of the liuing, which is the <hi>firſt particular penaltie,</hi> the <hi>Exciſion. Euery tree not bringing forth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The firſt penalty an Exciſion.</note> 
               <hi>good fruit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>is hewen downe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe but conſider, I beſeech you the <hi>fearefulneſſe</hi> of this <hi>penaltie.</hi> True.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Aequa lege neceſsitas, <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Carm. lib. 3 Ode 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Sortitur inſigneis &amp; imos:</l>
               <l>Omne capax mouet vrna nomen.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>What man liueth and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89. 47. Hebr. 9. 27.</note> There is a Statute for it, <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori.</hi> It is appointed vnto all men once to die. <hi>Death</hi> is Gods <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtat. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Ep.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> vnto whoſe <hi>arreſt</hi> the whole ſurui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing race of <hi>Adam</hi> is ſubiect, as well the godly as the vngodly: and therfore it is not here ſaid, that he which <hi>bringeth not forth good fruit,</hi> ſhall <hi>dye;</hi> but ſhall be <hi>hewen downe;</hi> to ſignifie the <hi>fearefulneſſe</hi> of that <hi>death</hi> which ſhall befall him. The <hi>godly</hi> man, hee that <hi>bringeth forth good</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:177608:31"/> 
               <hi>fruit,</hi> ſhal <hi>die:</hi> but he is <hi>happy</hi> in his <hi>end:</hi> for that he departeth this life in the <hi>ſweet peace of conſcience,</hi> which he hath obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſts blood,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is <hi>reconciled</hi> vnto God, &amp; <hi>ſealed vp</hi> vnto the day of <hi>redemption:</hi> ſo that the <hi>miſery of death</hi> is vnto him the <hi>death of all miſery,</hi> and his <hi>laſt end</hi> the <hi>beginning,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dies iſle quem tanquam extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum reformidas aeterninatalis eſt.</hi> Sen. Ep. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> the <hi>birth day of eternity.</hi> And therefore <hi>laetus lethu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excipit,</hi> come Death when it <hi>wil come,</hi> it is truly &amp; heartily <hi>welcome,</hi> &amp; finds him ready &amp; willing with much vnfained ioy to entertaine the <hi>ſtroke</hi> which ſhal ſeparat his ſoule &amp; body, that ſo being freed from the priſon of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he may <hi>enter into his maſters ioy,</hi> &amp; be <note place="margin">Matth. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.</note> crownd with glory &amp; happineſſe in the higheſt heauens. In regard wherof, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſius dum per m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntem evita tollitur, non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciditur, ſed ia vberius ſolum transfertur.</hi> Fran. Luc. Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens <hi>in locum</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>by Death</hi> he is taken out of this <hi>life,</hi> he cannot be ſaid to be <hi>hewen down,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>tranſplanted</hi> into a <hi>more fruitful ſoile.</hi> On the other ſide, the <hi>vngodly</hi> man, that <hi>bringeth not forth good fruit,</hi> but is <hi>barren</hi> in all goodneſſe, and only <hi>fruitfull</hi> in the <hi>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable works</hi> of <hi>darknes,</hi> he ſhal <hi>die,</hi> but a <hi>death</hi> far <hi>different</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: for being beſotted with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſinne, and hauing his <hi>affections</hi> faſt glewed to the things of this <hi>world,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177608:32"/> when <hi>Death arreſteth</hi> his <hi>Body,</hi> his <hi>Soule</hi> wil depart out of it like <hi>ſawduſt</hi> grated out of the belly of an <hi>hard Oke,</hi> with much labour and ſtriuing: ſo <hi>vnwilling</hi> and <hi>loth</hi> it will be to <hi>breake vp houſe,</hi> and bid farewell vnto the world. Yea, for as much as he neuer endeuoured to keep a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> toward God and man, therefore his <hi>guiltie Conſcience,</hi> like the <hi>euill Spirit</hi> which vexed <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhall moſt <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 14.</note> 
               <hi>fearefully wracke</hi> and <hi>torture</hi> him, and <hi>a wounded ſpirit who can beare?</hi> ſaith the <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 14.</note> Prouerbialiſt: and thus in the <hi>anguiſh</hi> and <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> of his <hi>Soule</hi> he ſhalbe <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 24. 20.</note> 
               <hi>like a tree:</hi> the <hi>Axe</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> ſhall <hi>cleaue</hi> &amp; <hi>rent</hi> his ſoule and body aſunder with all violence and terror, he <hi>ſhall bee hewen downe,</hi> ſaith my Text.</p>
            <p>But is this all? ſhall this <hi>Tree</hi> thus fell'd, there lie and reſt and rot where it falleth? I meane, ſhall his <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>body</hi> thus parted, ſo periſh, as that he ſhall ceaſe euer to haue a <hi>being</hi> any more, and conſequently a <hi>feeling</hi> of any further <hi>miſery?</hi> Certainly, though ſinful man be <hi>likevnto the beaſts that periſh,</hi> yet he doth <hi>not periſh like the beaſts,</hi> whoſe bodies are turned into aſhes, and their ſpirits va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as ſoft ayre, and are no more. No,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177608:32"/> his <hi>ſoule</hi> is an immortall ſubſtance, and his <hi>body,</hi> though in the eye of a carnall <hi>Sadducee,</hi> it ſeemeth ſo to periſh, as that it ſhall neuer haue a <hi>being</hi> any more; yet it ſhall at the laſt day by the power of God be reſtored to its iuſt proportion: for after <hi>Death</hi> there muſt come a <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment particular</hi> of the Soule, when it <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth</hi> from the body; <hi>generall,</hi> of Soule and body at the generall <hi>reſurrection.</hi> So that this fearfull <hi>hewing downe</hi> is but as the <hi>Prologue</hi> to a more <hi>tragicall</hi> &amp; <hi>feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Scene:</hi> it is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of <hi>ſorrowes,</hi> the forerunner of more fearefull torments. For after the <hi>axe</hi> of Death hath with all violence, <hi>cleft</hi> and <hi>rent</hi> his Soule and Body in ſunder, after that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee is <hi>thus hewen downe,</hi> it followeth in the next place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hee is caſt into the fire,</hi> hee is throwen headlong into the flames of Hell.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>ſecond penaltie,</hi> his <hi>exaſtion,</hi> is <note place="margin">The ſecond p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſtion.</note> indeed principally that which cauſeth his <hi>diſſolution</hi> to be ſo comfortles &amp; <hi>full of terrour.</hi> For when the hand of God lyeth heauy vpon him to <hi>hew</hi> him <hi>downe</hi> by <hi>death,</hi> it is not the ſeparation of his ſoule &amp; body that doth ſo much trouble
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177608:33"/> him, nor the leauing his beloued world that doth ſo much afflict him, no, nor the cruel gnawings of his guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence that doe ſo wrack &amp; torture him, otherwiſe then ioyned with the <hi>preſent apprehenſion</hi> of being <hi>caſt into</hi> this <hi>fire,</hi> which he then foreſeeth will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly befal him <hi>after his diſſolution.</hi> And no maruell, if the <hi>apprehenſion</hi> thereof ſtrike ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dread</hi> &amp; <hi>terror</hi> into his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting <note place="margin">Ethic. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> ſoule: for what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that <hi>heathen oracle</hi> of <hi>learning</hi> ſaid of the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death</hi> of the Body, as one who ſaw no farther then the <hi>twilight of Nature</hi> would giue him leane, may more truely be auerred of this <hi>ſecond penalty,</hi> that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>moſt terrible</hi> of <hi>terribles.</hi> As <hi>Zeuxis</hi> that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>painter</hi> deſiring to draw <hi>Junocs picture</hi> exactly, viewed al the <hi>Agrigentine Virgins</hi> with a <hi>curious</hi> eye, pickt out ſiue of the <hi>choyceſt Pieces</hi> Nature did afford amongſt them, out of which, for the compoſition of her pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he abſtracted and expreſſed with his pencill what he apprehended more accurate and excellent, either for <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> or <hi>beauty:</hi> So the liuelieſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance can be framed of this <hi>fearfull pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty,</hi> is by preſenting vnto our fantaſie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177608:33"/> all the torments that euer ſeized vpon the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> in this <hi>vally</hi> of <hi>miſery;</hi> and out of them to make choice of ſuch as are moſt <hi>exquiſite, acrimonious,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable,</hi> and out of theſe, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to extract a <hi>Quinteſſence,</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict this <hi>quinteſſence</hi> of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon <hi>one man:</hi> and yet when we haue done <hi>all this,</hi> this <hi>all</hi> is as <hi>nothing:</hi> we ſhall haue framed but a <hi>dull,</hi> a <hi>weake Idea</hi> of this <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</hi> For the Eie hath not ſeen, the Eare heard, nor hath it entred into the Heart of Man, <hi>as</hi> what <hi>ioyes</hi> God hath prepar'd <note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.</note> for thoſe that <hi>loue him, ſo</hi> what <hi>ſorrowes</hi> he hath laid vp for thoſe that <hi>leaue him.</hi> And therfore as the <hi>Painter</hi> preſenting the ſorrow of the father of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> when ſhe was to be ſacrificed, drew him with his <hi>face couered,</hi> as confeſsing his Art <hi>inſufficient</hi> to expreſſe in his viſage a griefe of that degree: ſo being at this time, according to my propounded <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> to preſent ſo <hi>terrible</hi> &amp; <hi>fearfull</hi> a <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie,</hi> as to be <hi>caſt into hell fire,</hi> my beſt courſe, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, were to caſt ouer it the <hi>vaile</hi> of <hi>ſilence,</hi> as being beſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcious of my own inſufficiency, for a task of ſuch <hi>tranſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy.</hi> Yet vnwilling my particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>weaknes</hi> ſhould fruſtrate the generall
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177608:34"/> expectation of ſo <hi>Honourable</hi> an <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> And fearing my ſilence in a point of <hi>ſuch importance</hi> may occaſion ſome to ſleight their owne ruine and neglect their <hi>ſpeedy reformation:</hi> For ſuch is naturally our ſlauiſh diſpoſition that (notwithſtanding all the gracious and glorious promiſes of the Goſpell) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the <hi>terrors</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> be punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally propounded vnto the <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and ſo reflect and beate vpon the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> wee walke without either <hi>feare</hi> or <hi>wit</hi> in the wayes of vngod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and as if wee had taken a liberall <hi>Doſis</hi> of <hi>Opium,</hi> are caſt into a <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Lethargie,</hi> and fall into <hi>Hell</hi> before we ſo much as <hi>dreame</hi> of <hi>Damnation.</hi> Therefore a word or two more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for the deſcription of the <hi>feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of this particular <hi>penaltie:</hi> For I intend not, though the caſe might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require it, to entertaine you with a particular diſcourſe of the <hi>ſeuerall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi> wherein all the powers and parts of each damned Wretch to his <hi>greater terror</hi> ſhall haue their ſhare; as thoſe Poſitiue of <hi>intollerable cold,</hi> the <hi>Worme</hi> that <hi>neuer dyeth, palpable darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the <hi>horrid aſpect</hi> of the <hi>Deuils,</hi> and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177608:34"/> infinite moe, the <hi>leaſt</hi> of all which is <hi>moſt horrible,</hi> too heauie for Nature to <note place="margin">Pector<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eroſo non tam moleſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſtrerum augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtia premi, quam abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; gloria pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uari. <hi>Stapl. promp. mor.</hi> Mali non tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dolebunt de ipſo tormento, quam quod repellentur a tali conſortio. <hi>Ludolph.</hi> Si nulla exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na poena torque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret haec ſola ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>Meſtreth ex Chryloſt.</hi>
               </note> ſuſtaine in her greateſt ſtrength. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I ſpeake of the <hi>perpetuall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation</hi> of the bleſſed viſion of a moſt glorious God, and happy ſocietie of the holy Angels and glorified Saints: a <hi>penaltie</hi> by all <hi>Diuines</hi> both <hi>antique</hi> and <hi>neotericke</hi> determined to be more <hi>terrible</hi> and <hi>fearefull,</hi> then all the Poſitiue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries <hi>Hell,</hi> yea <hi>tenne thouſand Hells</hi> can affoord. The large and learned la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Others concerning theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ſhall at this time ſaue me a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. I would gladly draw towards a concluſion, and therefore muſt deſire ſo much fauour as that I may confine my ſelfe vnto this in my <hi>Text,</hi> as being moſt frequent in the Scripture, and of a Poſitiue torment the moſt <hi>fearefull</hi> and <hi>intollerable. Ex vngue Leonem.</hi> I ſhall in it giue you, as it were the <hi>length</hi> of <hi>Hercules foot,</hi> and ſo leaue you to gueſſe at the <hi>full pourtaiture</hi> of his <hi>whole body. The Tree which bringeth not forth good fruit ſhall be hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three things that do more <note place="margin">Hell fire moſt fearefull for three cauſes.</note> punctually diſcouer vnto vs the <hi>feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:177608:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:177608:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:177608:36"/> of this <hi>Penaltie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The firſt is the <hi>Extremitie</hi> of it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </q>
            <p>Many are the torments which cruell <note place="margin">Multa ſunt ab hominibus exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitata ſupplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed nullum acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, nullum vc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementius, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum acrius igut. <hi>Bella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de gem Columb. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tyrants</hi> the Deuils <hi>Engineers</hi> haue fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the <hi>forge</hi> of their helliſh inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make poore <hi>Nature</hi> ſuffer: But of all; there is none more <hi>acute,</hi> none more <hi>vehement,</hi> none more <hi>acrimonious</hi> then that which is effected by <hi>Fire;</hi> and yet for extremity of heat, ſo infinite are the degrees whereby this <hi>Hell fire</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth our <hi>Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th fire,</hi> that the moſt expert <hi>Mathematician</hi> is vnable to take their <hi>true diſtance. Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> Furnace, though heated<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſeauen times</hi> more then ordinary, yet it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the <hi>extreme heate</hi> and <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour</hi> of <hi>this Fire</hi> is but as the <hi>Chill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmth</hi> of the Sunne in an <hi>extreme cold Winters day,</hi> or as the meere <hi>picture of Fire</hi> vnto the <hi>Fire</hi> which is <hi>Pictured: this Fire</hi> burneth in ſuch <hi>extremitie,</hi> that in it the <hi>leaſt moment</hi> of Paine will ſwallow vp whole <hi>Ages</hi> of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>fearefulneſſe</hi> of this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> appeareth in the <hi>Vniuerſalitie</hi> of it: <hi>this</hi> terrible <hi>Fire burneth</hi> not a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger onely, or a hand, or a foot, but the <note place="margin">Math. 10. 28.</note>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:177608:36"/> 
               <hi>whole body,</hi> yea, the <hi>whole man</hi> both <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſoule.</hi> For as <hi>both</hi> like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> haue beene brethten in the <hi>euill</hi> of <hi>Sinne:</hi> So <hi>both</hi> ſhall be brethren in the <hi>euil</hi> of <hi>ſuffering, both</hi> ſhal be <hi>tormented</hi> in this <hi>Flame,</hi> be <hi>caſt into</hi> this <hi>Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>fearefulnes</hi> of this <hi>Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> appeareth in the <hi>Perpetuitie</hi> of it. Though the <hi>whole man</hi> be extremely &amp; terribly tortured, yet it were ſome com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort if this <hi>acrimonious</hi> Penalty might haue either ſome <hi>ende</hi> or ſome <hi>eaſe.</hi> In <hi>Corporall griefs</hi> it is an experimentall <hi>Maxime,</hi> &amp; miniſtreth ſome <hi>comfort</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſick Patient, a Diſeaſe the <hi>ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lere &amp; di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Seneca <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p</hi> 78. Praceps mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus alterum facie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, aut exu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aut exting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Do'or qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ineita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to cuius in aliena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ione flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hoc ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſolatum eſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oris quod neceſſe est deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas illum ſentire ſi nimis ſenſiris. <hi>Senec. Ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> the <hi>ſhorter:</hi> the <hi>more violent,</hi> the <hi>leſſe permanent.</hi> It is impoſsible (ſaith <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca)</hi> for a man to be <hi>in great paine</hi> and a <hi>great while in paine:</hi> for either <hi>it</hi> wil <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly leaue</hi> Him, or <hi>He ſuddenly leaue it.</hi> And if neither his Diſeaſe be ſuddenly taken from him, nor he from his deſeaſe; yet certainly his <hi>Paine</hi> cannot long con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue in extremity, but will at length be tranſlated into a ſtupiditie; it will produce a <hi>Stupefaction</hi> and <hi>numneſſe</hi> in the parts it affecteth: and ſo the <hi>Partie</hi> ouerſenſibly affected ceaſeth to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his griefe.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:177608:37"/>
            <p>Againe a <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>virulent</hi> Diſeaſe though it be a long time ere a man can wholly ſhake it off and bid it farewell, ſometime not till his <hi>laſt of time,</hi> (Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes <note place="margin">Silongus eſt, habet intercape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, dat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiom locu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> multum tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris donat, neceſſe eſt vt exurgat &amp; deſimat. Jdem ibidem.</note> commonly <hi>comming on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe,</hi> but <hi>going away on foote)</hi> yet it is no ſmall comfort vnto the ſicke Patient that it commeth but by <hi>fitts:</hi> it doth not keep a <hi>continuall Terme</hi> in his body but hath ſometimes its <hi>receſſes</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations:</hi> it doth not alwayes <hi>ſit in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion;</hi> ſometimes it hath an <hi>intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and leaueth <hi>Man</hi> to himſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect his ſcattered ſpirits, and repaire the ruined and craſie walls of his <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacle,</hi> whereby he is the better enabled to hold out againſt the furious aſſaults thereof.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there are diuers <hi>artificiall Confections</hi> which the skilfull in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke are able to preſcribe and prepare, if not for the <hi>extirpation</hi> of his diſeaſe, yet at leaſt for the <hi>remiſsion</hi> and <hi>mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Paine: there are <hi>lenitiues</hi> to aſſwage and quallifie the <hi>raging madnes</hi> thereof. Howſoeuer at length that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike <hi>Eſculapius</hi> Doctor <hi>Death</hi> will one day viſit the perplexed <hi>Patient,</hi> and giue him a <hi>dyet drink</hi> that will vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177608:37"/> cure him of <hi>all his griefes.</hi> Thus, I ſay, though a man bee infeſted with a diſeaſe that doth extremely plague and torture him, yet he hath theſe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>helpes</hi> to ſuſtaine him in it: either He and his Diſeaſe will ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly take their laſt farewell one of an other; or if it continue any time with him, it will in proceſſe of time, through <hi>extremity of pain,</hi> produce a <hi>ſtupefaction,</hi> or admit of ſome friendly <hi>intermiſsion,</hi> or at leaſt of ſome gentle <hi>remiſsion,</hi> to make it the more ſupportable: howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the Patient and his paine muſt one day part, and then there is <hi>an end</hi> of <hi>all</hi> his <hi>ſorrowes.</hi> But alas, it is not ſo here, he that is <hi>caſt into this fire,</hi> is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the leaſt of all theſe comforts: for the <hi>extremity</hi> of his <hi>paine</hi> is <hi>perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> his <hi>torments</hi> are both <hi>endles</hi> &amp; <hi>eaſeles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was indeed the opinion of <hi>Origen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib, 21. de Ciuitate Dei, Cap 17.</note> and his Diſciples, that <hi>all</hi> the <hi>damned,</hi> yea, euen the <hi>Deuils</hi> themſelues, ſhould one day be abſolued from their paines, <note place="margin">Tanto inuenitur erra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; contra Des ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, quanto ſibi videtur ſentire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lementius <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. ibidem.</hi>
               </note> and receiued into the ſoci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie of the Saints: which though it be a very <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful opinion,</hi> yet it is a very <hi>foule errour,</hi> and hath bin therefore iuſtly exploded by the Church, as contradicting both
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177608:38"/> 
               <hi>reaſon,</hi> and plaine text of <hi>Scripture. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> requireth a correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy between the reward of righteouſnes, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of iniquitie: that as he which like a <hi>good tree bringeth forth good fruit,</hi> ſhall be remoued from earth to heauen, there to inherite <hi>euerlaſting felicitie:</hi> ſo hee which like a <hi>bad tree, doth not bring forth good fruit,</hi> ſhould be <hi>cut downe</hi> from off the face of the earth, and <hi>caſt</hi> into <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall miſery.</hi> And the ſacred <hi>Scripture</hi> doth plainly informe vs that <hi>Exinfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no nulla redemptio,</hi> from Hell there is no redemption: As none can go from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to Hell, ſo none can goe from Hell <note place="margin">Luke 16. 26.</note> to Heauen; No, their heauineſſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall, their plague deſperate, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee cured. The <hi>breath</hi> of the Lord like a <hi>riuer of brimſtone,</hi> doth kindle the <note place="margin">Eſay 30. 33.</note> fire of Hell; and being once kindled, it neuer either of it ſelfe goeth out, or can be put out: for it is fire <hi>euerlaſting</hi> and <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. 41 Eſay 66. Exod. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>vnquenchable:</hi> and whoſoeuer is call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, like <hi>Moſes</hi> buſh, ſhal be <hi>burned,</hi> but <hi>neuer conſumed:</hi> he ſhall there continue <hi>eternally</hi> both body &amp; ſoule in vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſery. The <hi>extremitie</hi> of his paine ſhall not produce in him the leaſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefaction: for he ſhall be <hi>eternally</hi> and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177608:38"/> 
               <hi>totally</hi> perfectly ſenſible of this fire. His paine ſhall not admit of the leaſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, or remiſsion there ſhal not be the leaſt moment of time, but in which he ſhall feelingly confeſſe, <hi>I am moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely and fearefully tormented in this flame.</hi> He ſhall not obtaine ſo much as a <hi>drop of cold water</hi> in the eternity of his extremity, <hi>to coole the tip of his tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no ſmal content vnto one that is afflicted with a violent burning Feuer, that he can turne and tumble himſelfe too and fro in his bed in a vaine hope of eaſe: But <hi>Hee</hi> that is <hi>caſt into this fire,</hi> ſhall be no more able to moue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then a <hi>Tree that is hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> For ſeeing that <note place="margin">Jiqui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>unt vincu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m pent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> liga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nibus &amp; pedibus mitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in panan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aeternam. <hi>Guil. Pariſ. Math.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liquod ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> habuiſſe doloris. <hi>Iob</hi> 16. 12.</note> through his diſſolute courſe of life hee often broke the Chaine of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: he ſhall therfore by Gods commandement be faſt tyed hand and foot wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch chaines as hee ſhall not be able to breake: thus bound he ſhall be <hi>caſt into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas in <hi>Miſerie</hi> it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſome <hi>Comfort</hi> to haue <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:</hi> Hee that is <hi>caſt into this Fire,</hi> ſhall indeed haue <hi>Companie,</hi> but ſuch as (like <hi>Iobs</hi> friends) will proue vnto
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177608:39"/> him but <hi>miſerable comforters:</hi> their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhall be ſo little for his conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that it ſhal much conduce for the augmenting his affliction. For (not to ſpeake of the <hi>horrid aspect</hi> of his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors, and the <hi>fearfull howlings</hi> of the Tormented) hee ſhall then ſee thoſe in hell with him, of whoſe damnation him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was the procuring cauſe: and this ſhall adde infinitely to his paines: for as <hi>Hee,</hi> who by his godly counſell, and religious conuerſation hath bin an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, to conuert others vnto God, ſhall <hi>ſhine as the ſtarres in the firmament,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 12. 13.</note> haue a peculiar reward of glory aboue others: ſo <hi>Hee</hi> who by his wicked and lewd conuerſation hath occaſioned the fal of others, ſhal for <hi>it,</hi> beſides his more generall paines, haue ſome more <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all torment</hi> inflicted vpon him: ſo that the very ſight of ſuch for whoſe ſake he ſuſtaineth his peculiar torments, ſhall bring no ſmall affliction to his Soule. And hence it was (as <hi>Diuines</hi> haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) that <hi>Diues</hi> being in <hi>Hell fire,</hi> requeſted <hi>Abraham</hi> to diſpatch <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 16. 27, 28.</note> to his Fathers houſe, to premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Brethren, that they might not come into that place of Torment:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177608:39"/> not for any good hee intended toward his Brethren, (for Hell is as farre from Charitie, as Heauen from Enuy) but out of feare leſt his paines ſhould bee augmented through <hi>their preſence,</hi> hee hauing corrupted them by his bad example.</p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Sicut nihil in Coelo deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Simon Pauli Sucrinenſis.</note> 
               <hi>quod non inuenitur: it a nihil in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferno inuenitur quod deſideratur:</hi> as in Heauen there is nothing deſired which is not found: ſo in Hell there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing found which is deſired. <hi>He</hi> that <note place="margin">Dabitur miſeris vita mortalis, mori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntur &amp; ſemper erunt. <hi>Caſſiodorus. Reuel.</hi> 9. 6.</note> is caſt into Hell fire, <hi>ſhall ſeeke Death, but ſhall not finde it: hee ſhall deſire to dye, but Death ſhall flee from him:</hi> Hell ſhall deſire <hi>eaſe,</hi> but bee ſo farre from the leaſt hope of obtaining it, that whether the preſent paine hee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth in ſuch <hi>extremitie,</hi> by vertue of <hi>this fire,</hi> or the <hi>preſent thought</hi> of the <hi>perpetuitie</hi> thereof be his greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, it is hard to determine.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that this <hi>penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> is <hi>Paradoxicall</hi> to naturall Reaſon: for firſt, it being a Poſition in <hi>Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie,</hi> That the <hi>Agent is more Noble then the Patient,</hi> how can this <hi>Fire</hi> which is generally held <hi>Corporeall,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177608:40"/> the Soule which is <hi>Spirituall?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this <hi>Fire</hi> being of a <hi>deuouring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 33. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>nature,</hi> how can it burne the Body; and not at length conſume and reduce it to nothing, the body being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally as combuſtible as Chaffe? Heere indeed is Saint <hi>Pauls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> as <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> in another caſe: ſo muſt I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in this, <hi>Quò diutiùs mecum cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>òmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ùs inuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o:</hi> The more I ſeeke into it, the more I am to ſeeke in it: It is a <hi>great Myſterie,</hi> a <hi>Gordian Knot,</hi> which naturall <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot vntye. What Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for the former <hi>Quaere, Fit miris, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d veris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>modis,</hi> may alſo ſatisfie for the latter. That this <hi>Corporeall Fire</hi> doeth afflict the Soule, which is <hi>Spirituall:</hi> that it <hi>continually burneth</hi> the Body, but <hi>neuer conſumeth</hi> it, is not <hi>more ſtrange</hi> then true. The ſame Father, for the <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> nibus v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt one ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ne,—p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Creator<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, <hi>ib. c.</hi> 9.</note> of our <hi>Faith</hi> in this poynt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth in diuers Creatures, and more particularly the <hi>Salamander,</hi> that doth miraculouſly liue in the fire without being conſumed. <hi>Mans weakeneſſe</hi> is vnable to determine the <hi>power of God,</hi> it exceeding all that wee can poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apprehend. Theſe therefore being
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177608:40"/> 
               <hi>ineffable Myſteries,</hi> are not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the ſcantling of naturall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Our beſt courſe is to <hi>beleeue it here,</hi> leſt for our vnbeliefe wee be made to <hi>feele it hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may bee replyed, That to puniſh Man <hi>eternally,</hi> who ſinned but <hi>temporally,</hi> may argue God of <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> and <hi>Crueltie.</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> doth excellently well demonſtrate the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie</hi> of this <hi>Penaltie.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Iniqui cum fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, quia cum fine vixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> nam volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> viue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, vt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſent ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap> Oſtendunt enim quodm p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p unt, qui nurqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de, inunt pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>Greg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Dialog</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>icti i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntentiam per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cant ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> men, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; nullus deturn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui quam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>uit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Greg. 3. lib. Moral.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>The wicked,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſinne but for a time, becauſe they liue but for a time: By their good willes they would neuer dye, that they might euer ſinne: For they ſhewe they would euer liue in Sinne, becauſe they neuer leaue ſinning ſo long as they liue.</hi> And therefore, as hee elſewhere ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: * <hi>It ſtandeth with the Iuſtice of</hi> God, <hi>to viſite man with a perpetuall Penaltie, who if hee might would liue perpetually in Iniquitie.</hi> Beſides, Man in ſinning offendeth an <hi>Infinite Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> and therefore in all equitie deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an <hi>infinite miſery,</hi> to bee afflicted with <hi>endleſſe torments.</hi> But why doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtand diſputing vpon the equity of this penalty? as if it were a fit thing to cal God to an account for his Iudgements</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:177608:41"/>
            <p>Certainly though they be <hi>ſecret,</hi> yet they can <hi>neuer</hi> be <hi>vniuſt,</hi> for as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 25.</note> vnto <hi>God; Shall not the Iudge of all the world doe right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then the <hi>fearefulneſſe</hi> of that <hi>Penalty</hi> which God will after this life inflict vpon ſinnefull man: he ſhall be <hi>caſt into Hell fire,</hi> there to be tormented <hi>extremly,</hi> to be <hi>extremely</hi> tormented <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally,</hi> to be <hi>extremely</hi> and <hi>totally</hi> tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>eternally.</hi> O what an <hi>eating torment</hi> is but the aking of a <hi>Tooth?</hi> What a <hi>ſharpe</hi> and <hi>piercing paine</hi> to hold but a <hi>finger</hi> in the <hi>fire:</hi> but to be <hi>all</hi> on <hi>fire</hi> of <hi>Hell?</hi> to haue no part <hi>free?</hi> for the <hi>whole man</hi> to be nothing elſe but a <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in <hi>extremitie,</hi> and ſo to continue without the <hi>leaſt hope</hi> of <hi>eaſe</hi> world without end? We cannot but appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and confeſſe an <hi>intollerable</hi> an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſsible penaltie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to what purpoſe doe I labour to ſet forth the <hi>fearfulneſſe</hi> of this <hi>penalty?</hi> When we ſpeake of theſe things, doe we not participate of <hi>Caſſandraes bleſsing?</hi> Though wee ſpeake the truth and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the truth, yet as the Prophet complaineth, <hi>Who will beleeue our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 53. 2.</note> Or at leaſt who will be <hi>reformed</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177608:41"/> by it? If we conſult with the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſinnefulneſſe of this age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue, the horrible ſecuritie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thoſe outragious and vnheard of villanies euery where practiſed and perpetrated euen in the <hi>eye</hi> of the <hi>Sunn,</hi> it will plainely appeare that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of mankind take <hi>Hell fire</hi> to be but <hi>Inane terriculamentum,</hi> a ſilly <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crow</hi> to keepe man in awe and order, an <hi>Old wiues fable,</hi> a meere <hi>Poeticall fiction:</hi> ſo little doth it preuaile with them for their reformation: Certainly, <hi>My be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,</hi> were our <hi>beliefe</hi> in this point <hi>as ſound</hi> and our <hi>Meditation</hi> thereon <hi>as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> as our <hi>liuing</hi> is <hi>ſinnefull;</hi> O, what a holy and bleſſed <hi>change</hi> would it work both in our <hi>conſciences</hi> and <hi>conuerſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tully</hi> writeth of one <hi>Damocles</hi> a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiticall <note place="margin">Tuſcul. lib 5.</note> Courtier, that though placed in the Seat-royall of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and preſented with a banquet of the choyceſt rarities, and to wrap vp the whole Hiſtory in a word, liberally furniſhed with whatſoeuer his heart could deſire for the accompliſhment of his <hi>conceited happineſſe,</hi> yet when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing his eyes about him he eſpied a <hi>glittering Sword</hi> hanging ouer his head
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177608:42"/> in a <hi>Horſe haire</hi> ready to cleaue &amp; ſpilt him in twaine euery moment. Which as the former, was done at the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> to let him ſee his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rour, that he behold his <hi>happineſſe</hi> in a <hi>falſe Glaſſe.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt feare of his imminent danger did ſo <hi>captiuate</hi> his <hi>freer iollitie,</hi> that hee then began <hi>extremely to loath</hi> what before he did ſo <hi>entirely loue:</hi> his delicate iuncates were vnto him but as <hi>vnſauory viands,</hi> and his del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtfull obiects but as <hi>muſick</hi> in a time of <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> he then had rather part with his happineſſe vpon <hi>euen termes,</hi> then pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it at <hi>ſo deare a price.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner though naturally we are <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>finitly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted</hi> in following the <hi>luſts of our owne hearts,</hi> and repute it the onely happines that can befall v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> freely to diſport our ſelues in all <hi>licenciouſneſſe:</hi> Yet if wee did but deliberately weigh our owne caſe, as indeed it neerely concerneth vs ſo to doe, Laying the <hi>pleaſures of ſinne</hi> which can laſt but for a little ſeaſon in <hi>one Scale</hi> and the <hi>Penaltie</hi> for ſin which will hold out to <hi>eternity</hi> in the <hi>other;</hi> if wee did but ſeriouſly conſider that the <hi>wrath of God is reuealed from Heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>all vngodlineſſe and vnrighteouſnes</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177608:42"/> 
               <hi>of men,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: that the <hi>Lord hath whet his Sword, and bent his Bow, and hath made his inſtruments</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 7. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ready to wound the hayrie Scalpe of him that goeth on in his wickedneſſe,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh. That the <hi>axe</hi> of <hi>his wrath</hi> is <hi>already laid vnto the roote of the Trees,</hi> and that hee is reſolutely determined that thoſe <hi>Trees,</hi> thoſe <hi>Men</hi> which <hi>bring not forth good fruit ſhal be hewen downe and caſt into the fire,</hi> into Hell Fire, there to be <hi>extremely</hi> and <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally</hi> tormented <hi>eternally,</hi> it would beget in our hearts a mortall hatred euen of our boſome and beſt beloued corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and worke with vs euen in the middeſt of our ſinfull pleaſures as the <hi>Handwriting</hi> vpon the <hi>Wall</hi> with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5. 6.</note> in the midſt of his Iollitie: it would cauſe our <hi>countenance</hi> to be <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> our <hi>thoughts</hi> to <hi>trouble</hi> vs, the <hi>ioynts</hi> of our <hi>loines</hi> to be <hi>looſed,</hi> and our <hi>knees</hi> to <hi>ſmite</hi> one againſt the other: it would make vs with the <hi>Iailor</hi> to tremble and and fall before the Miniſters of God, &amp; <note place="margin">Acts 16. 29. 30.</note> ſay, <hi>Sirs what ſhall we doe to bee ſaued?</hi> Oh, it is a terrible and fearefull thing <note place="margin">Raro anteceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſcelestum deſeruit pede paena claudo. <hi>Car. lib 3. ode 2</hi>
               </note> to fall into the hands of the liuing God.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177608:43"/> Though hee hath <hi>leaden</hi> heeles, yet hee hath <hi>iron</hi> hands. <hi>Serò ſed ſerio,</hi> He is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <note place="margin">Tarditatem vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictae Supplic ij grauitate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſat.</note> ſlow to proceed in Iudgment, but when he comes, as come hee will, hee ſtrikes home, and layes it on heauily. Therefore, <hi>my Beloued,</hi> let vs take heed <note place="margin">The certaintie of the pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we doe not dally with God, and ſlight his terrible Iudgements, as if they did nothing concerne vs: for that the Lord will render vengeance vnto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience, and viſit the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of impudent and impenitent ſinners with the intollerable eternall torments of hell fire, is a truth as cleare as that God is truth: wee haue it deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from his <hi>own mouth,</hi> and recorded vnder his <hi>owne hand:</hi> his ſacred Word endited by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> hath moſt clearely reuealed it vnto vs; and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe, we may venture to <hi>take his word</hi> and build vpon it: for <hi>God is not as man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23. 19.</note> 
               <hi>that hee ſhould lye, neither as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent: hath hee ſayd, and ſhall he not doe it? and hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it?</hi> Certainly, <hi>Heauen and Earth ſhall ſooner paſſe away,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 16. 17.</note> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>then the leaſt iot or title of the Law ſhall fall.</hi> And therefore the <hi>penaltie</hi> here threatned, ſhal <hi>moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:177608:43"/> be <hi>inflicted.</hi> Yea, to intimate the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted certaintie</hi> thereof, it is not heere ſaid in the future Tenſe, The tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, <hi>ſhall bee hewen downe and caſt into the fire,</hi> but <hi>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewen downe and caſt into the fire:</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as certaine, as if it were already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: So <hi>hee which beleeueth not, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 18.</note> 
               <hi>condemned,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour. The <hi>Law</hi> hath already denounced the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>malediction</hi> againſt the Sinner, <hi>Curſed is hee that confirmeth not all the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 27. 26.</note> 
               <hi>words of the Law to doe them:</hi> And what the curſe of the law is, is not vnknown to the verieſt <hi>Babe</hi> in <hi>Chriſtianitie:</hi> it is the eternall deſtruction of body and ſoule in hell fire. So that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting vnto the certaintie of this Penaltie, but a <hi>more ſolemne declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and a <hi>reall execution</hi> thereof: which ſhall be <hi>then</hi> effected, <hi>when</hi> the Sonne of man our Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhall come in the clouds in his Glory accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all his holy Angels, to iudge the quicke and the dead: then ſhall hee pronounce that dreadfull Sentence of condemnation, <hi>Diſcedite a me maledicti,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 41.</note> Depart from me ye curſed into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire, which is prepared for the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177608:44"/> Diuell and his Angels, and <hi>then</hi> ſhall it be put into execution, for they <hi>ſhall goe</hi> into euerlaſting torments, <hi>verſe</hi> 46</p>
            <p>And let no man delighting in <hi>impiety</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Generalitie or exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Penaltie</note> delude his own ſoule with a vaine hope of <hi>impunitie;</hi> let him <hi>not thinke to eſcape the iudgement of God, whileſt he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1 32.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch things as are worthy of death:</hi> for the Lord is a <hi>powerfull</hi> and an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall</hi> Iudge: <hi>Who can ſtand before his wrath? or who can abide the fierceneſſe of his wrath? His wrath is powred out like fire, and the very Rocks are broken by him,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. King <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> though a moſt puiſſant Prince, a <hi>great Tree,</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſtiles him, <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 11.</note> ſtrong and high vnto heauen, in whoſe boughes the Birds of the ayre did build their neſts, yet ſaw in a Viſion a <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> a <hi>holy One</hi> comming downe from <note place="margin">Verſe 14.</note> Heauen, who cried alowd <hi>Succidite ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem,</hi> Hew downe the <hi>Tree</hi> and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it. <hi>Tophet is prepared for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 30. 33.</note> 
               <hi>King,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay. Though his excellencie mount vp vnto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and his head reach vp to the clouds, yet ſhall he periſh for euer like his owne dung,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 20. 6. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177608:44"/>
               <l>Regum timendorum in proprios greges,</l>
               <l>Reges in ipſos imperium eſt Iouis, <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. Carm. lib. 3. Ode, 1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Clari Gygant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o triumpho,</l>
               <l>cunsta ſupercilio mouentis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>God hath an <hi>vnreſiſtable power</hi> ouer the moſt Commanding Princes: <hi>By him Kings raigne, Princes, Nobles and all the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro 8. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Iudges of the earth doe rule,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> the greateſt Prince that euer ruled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth. <hi>At his foot ſtoole</hi> the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt <hi>Monarchs</hi> muſt lay downe their <hi>Crownes</hi> and make their appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his moſt dreadfull preſence, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting themſelues to be cenſured and ſentenced and ſuffer according to their demerits. God ſpareth <hi>none</hi> though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo mightie: yea, for <hi>that reſpect</hi> hee dealeth <hi>more ſharpely</hi> with them. For as <hi>Hieronimus Guadalupe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis</hi> vpon this <hi>Text</hi> obſerueth, The <hi>more Potent</hi> a man <note place="margin">Quanto quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> potentior ſinon ferat f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uctum tonto maiori d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnus est ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicio, qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio eſt multis non ferendi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos fructus. Scilicet in vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus manout ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regentum. <hi>Claudianus.</hi>
               </note> is, if he doe not bring forth good <hi>fruite,</hi> the <hi>greater puniſhment</hi> he deſerueth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He is an Occaſion vnto many of their not <hi>bringing forth good fruit:</hi> Men ordinarily ſuffering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected &amp; lob-led by the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of their Superiors, like the <hi>Spaniard</hi> that held his <hi>neck awry</hi> becauſe <hi>Alphonſo</hi> of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> his king was <hi>wry neckt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:177608:45"/>
            <p>It is no mans Greatnes that can ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him from the ſmoking ſhowre of Gods wrath. Euen that <hi>Mitred man of Sinne,</hi> which treadeth Scepters vnder his feet, and exalteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God, though hee plead both a <hi>canonizing</hi> and a <hi>confounding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> yet <hi>He</hi> alſo ſhall one day be brought before the <hi>Barre</hi> of Gods Iuſtice, to be arraigned for all his Abominations, wherewith he hath infatuated and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted both <hi>himſelfe</hi> and Gods <hi>Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and ſhall drinke of the <hi>dregges</hi> of Gods <hi>wrath cup,</hi> the promerited reward of his workes.</p>
            <p>And let no <hi>hood-winkt Catholike</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride this peremptory aſſertion, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a diſtempered braine: for I know what I ſay: If his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> cannot procure his owne immunitie from the paines of Purgatory, as for example, Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De Gemitu Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbae, li. 2. c. 9.</note> who as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> writeth, is to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue there till Doomes day: much leſſe ſhall he be able by his pretended power to deliuer himſelfe from hell fire. Now if theſe lofty <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and ſturdy <hi>Oakes</hi> of <hi>Baſan</hi> cannot auoid the ſtroke of the <hi>Axe,</hi> but ſhall be <hi>hewen</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:177608:45"/> 
               <hi>downe and caſt into the fire,</hi> what ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the <hi>leſſer trees,</hi> the <hi>lower ſhrubs?</hi> Certainly, God will be <hi>impartiall</hi> in his <hi>judiciary proceedings:</hi> his eye will ſpare none. <hi>Tribulation &amp; anguiſh vpon Euery</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. 11, 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſoule of man that doth euill, of the Jew firſt, and alſo of the Gentile. With him there is no respect of perſons: for as many as haue ſinned without the Law, ſhall alſo periſh without the Law: and as many as haue ſinned in the Law, ſhall bee iudged by the Law. God will wound the hairy ſcalpe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> 
               <hi>of Euery one that goeth on in his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid. The ſoule</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kiel 18. 4</note> 
               <hi>that ſinneth ſhall dye.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites</hi> could gull Captaine <hi>Ioſhua</hi> with <note place="margin">Ioſhua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 5.</note> their <hi>old ſhooes,</hi> their <hi>mouldy cruſtes,</hi> and <hi>thred bare garments,</hi> and ſo ſaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from his ſword: But God hath <hi>oculum in Sceptro,</hi> as he is <hi>omnipotent,</hi> ſo hee is <hi>omniſcient:</hi> he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <note place="margin">Pſalm. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 3.</note> Hearts ſearcher: he knoweth vs all, and all our wayes too well to be deceiued by vs. It is not the wearing of a <hi>Gyges</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cic. Oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic li. 3.</note> Ring can keepe vs out of Gods ſight: for there is nothing that hath a being in nature, which is not the obiect of his eye. <hi>If I ſay, Surely the darkeneſſe ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1 39. 11. 12</note> 
               <hi>couer me, euen the night ſhall bee a light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:177608:46"/> 
               <hi>me; yea, the darkneſſe hideth not from thee, but the night ſhineth as the day; the darkeneſſe and the light are both alike to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, when the Lord ſhall call the ſonnes of men to a <hi>particular account</hi> for their tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſgreſsions, then <hi>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſalus hominum,</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Mans helpe is all but in vaine. <hi>Though hand ioyne in hand,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, the wicked</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not eſcape vnpuniſhed:</hi> that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (ſaith our Engliſh Gloſſe) Though they make neuer ſo many friends, or thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues neuer ſo ſecure, yet they ſhall not eſcape. It is not the <hi>phantaſticall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of the Saints <hi>Supererogatiue workes</hi> vnder his Holineſſe locke and key can ſerue the ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers turne in that day: for the <hi>Wiſe Virgins</hi> could not lend any <note place="margin">Math. 25. 6.</note> Oyle, leſt they ſhould lacke for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. It is not any mans <hi>Potency</hi> can be his <hi>Protection:</hi> for the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Monarch is but as a <hi>Potters veſſell,</hi> eaſily broken into ſheards and ſhiuers with the leaſt touch of Gods <hi>yron rod.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. 27.</note> It is not the ſubtill pate of the deepeſt <hi>Politician</hi> can pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uaile for any man. For <hi>the wiſedome of the world is but fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 20. Eſay 29. 14.</note> 
               <hi>with God. I will deſtroy the wiſdome</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:177608:46"/> 
               <hi>of the wiſe, and will caſt away the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the prudent,</hi> ſaith the Lord. No courſe can be taken to diſappoynt God of his reuenging purpoſes: for as the Prophet hath it, <hi>The flight ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 2. 14, 15, 6.</note> 
               <hi>from the ſwift: and the ſtrong ſhall not ſtrengthen his force: neither ſhal the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſaue his life: nor hee that handleth the bowe ſhall ſtand: and hee that is ſwift of foot ſhall not eſcape, neither ſhall hee that rideth the horſe ſane his life: And he that is of a mightie courage among the ſtrong men, ſhall flee away naked in that day,</hi> ſaith the Lord. So that without any <note place="margin">Omnis ſine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, ſin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſationum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i cuius cuaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Gorth in lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> perſonall exception, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſiue allegation, without any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ones euaſion, <hi>Euery tree,</hi> euery man <hi>not bringing foorth good fruit,</hi> the fruits of holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe and ſanctification, <hi>ſhall be hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery tree not bringing forth <hi>Good fruit:</hi> Many in their own account paſſe for current Chriſtians, and are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they ſhall go for no leſſe with God, when they are called to giue vp their accounts vnto him, if they do <hi>not bring forth bad fruit:</hi> if like the <hi>proud Phariſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 18 11.</note> they can but plead for themſelues, <hi>Not guiltie as other</hi> men, <hi>Extortioners, vnjuſt,</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:177608:47"/> 
               <hi>adulterers:</hi> If they can ſay, We are no <hi>Drunkards,</hi> no <hi>Swearers,</hi> no <hi>ſpendthrifts,</hi> no <hi>grinders</hi> of the <hi>Poore,</hi> and the like: If like Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Herbe, which (as Cookes report) being put into the pot, procureth nor good nor hurt to the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: ſo if they <hi>doe no hurt,</hi> though they <hi>neuer do any good;</hi> if they be <hi>honeſt harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men,</hi> as they are commonly ſtiled, ſuch as neither meddle nor make with others: but liue quietly, (it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for religiouſly) among their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, all is well: they hope in God to goe to Heauen as ſure as the beſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, <hi>poore miſerable wretches,</hi> how pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably, how groſſely they deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>Ixion</hi>-like embracing a <hi>Cloud</hi> inſtead of <hi>Iuno:</hi> like <hi>Camelions</hi> fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon the <hi>ayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hope</hi> of that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe they ſhall neuer find. Indeed, <hi>Not to doe euill</hi> is <hi>commendable;</hi> but <hi>not to doe good,</hi> is <hi>culpable,</hi> is <hi>condemnable. Caſt the vnprofitable ſeruant into vtter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 25. 30.</note> 
               <hi>darkeneſſe: there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> And here in my text, Euery tree not bringing forth <hi>good fruit</hi> ſhall bee <hi>hewen downe,</hi> and <hi>caſt into the fire.</hi> Wee doe not reade that the <hi>Rich</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>man</hi> in the Goſpell diſpoyled <hi>Lazarus</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:177608:47"/> of any thing whereof he was poſſeſſed: yet becauſe he did not open vnto him the bowells of compaſsion, and cauſe to be tendered vnto him wherewith to ſuſtaine him in his want: therefore Hell mouth was opened to ſwallow him vp vnto euerlaſting torments.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon is this, wee read in <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sinne is the tranſgreſsion of the Law:</hi> and the <hi>tranſgreſsion</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>the wages of Sinne is Death.</hi> Now the Lords Mandates are as well <hi>Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> for the enſuing of Good, as <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> for the eſchewing of Euill: and the <hi>Affirmatiue</hi> as well as the <hi>Negatiue</hi> vnder the Curſe require <hi>exact obedience.</hi> So that, He is no leſſe lyable vnto the Laws malediction <hi>Quiomittit facienda,</hi> which omitteth things to be done, then <hi>Qui facit omittenda,</hi> He which doth things to bee omitted. The <hi>laſt</hi> and great <hi>Aſsiſes</hi> will fully and plainely reſolue this caſe, determine this point. <note place="margin">Matt. 25 41.</note> for, <hi>Then ſhall the Sonne of man ſay vnto the Goates on the left hand, Depart from me yee curſed into euerlaſting Fire prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Diuels and his Angels:</hi> Here is the Curſe. Heare wee the Cauſe: It
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177608:48"/> followeth, <hi>For I was an hungred, and yee gaue me no meate: I thirſted, and yee gaue me no drinke; I was naked, and yee clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me not: Sicke and in priſon, and yee viſited me not.</hi> Where we may ſee the bare <hi>omiſsion</hi> of the good works of <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> the <hi>procuring cauſe</hi> of perpetuall <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie:</hi> ratifying the Poſition in my Text, that euery <hi>Tree</hi> not bringing forth <hi>good fruit</hi> ſhall be <hi>hewen down and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Euery Tree</hi> not bringing forth forth <hi>good fruit</hi> ſhall be thus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: how fearefully ſhall it fare with thoſe trees that do not onely not bring foorth <hi>good fruit,</hi> but alſo bring forth <hi>bad fruite? Si ſola omiſsio eternoigne punitur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>vitioſa actio quid meretur?</hi> If the bare omiſſion and neglect of a pious office bee puniſhable with euerlaſting fire: what doth a vicious action deſerue? <hi>Si ſterilitas condemnatur, continuata im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietas, foeda delectatio, affectuoſa peccati proſecutio quam dirè torquebitur?</hi> If ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilitie and barrenneſſe be condemned: how direfully ſhall continued impietie, wallowing with delight in the ſtinking puddle of iniquitie, an affected proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of all vngodlineſſe euen with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177608:48"/> greedineſſe bee tortured and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented? If thoſe ſhall bee thruſt <note place="margin">Non mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oris eſt criminis h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>i tollere, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; habes indigen ibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egare. <hi>Ambr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n quedam Ser.</hi>
               </note> into Hell that haue not relieued the poore and needy in their want and miſerie; what ſhall be come of ſuch as lay violent hands vpon their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony? If ſuch neglect the performance of Religious duties whether towards <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man</hi> are guil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of euerlaſting damnation; How ſhall they eſcape the dreadfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God which like the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <note place="margin">Luke 184.</note> Iudge feare nor God, nor man: but liue in the wilfull breach of their Makers Lawes? If ſuch ſhall moſt certainely be condemned as are onely <hi>barren</hi> in <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> what ſhall be come of thoſe that are alſo <hi>fruitfull</hi> in the <hi>damnable workes</hi> of <hi>darkeneſſe?</hi> If the <hi>Figge tree</hi> for not bringing forth good <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. 21. 19.</note> fruit muſt bee curſed, how ſhall the <hi>Vines</hi> of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> eſcape <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 32, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which bring foorth <hi>bad fruite,</hi> fruite <hi>bitter</hi> as <hi>Gall, Deadly</hi> as the poiſon of <hi>Dragons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Conſider this all yee that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> your God, that forget your owne good in being <hi>ſtrangers from the life of God,</hi> leaſt the Lord in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177608:49"/> his wrath <hi>hew you downe,</hi> and there bee none to deliuer you. For if God ſpared not his bleſſed <hi>Angells,</hi> nor his beloued <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they brought forth the <hi>curſed fruit</hi> of <hi>rebellion</hi> and <hi>diſobedience:</hi> how ſhall hee ſpare vs that are but <hi>duſt and aſhes: Wormes</hi> and not Men: by Nature mere <hi>aliens from the Common wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the couenants of promiſe:</hi> ſeeing in lewdneſſe of life and Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation we are nothing inferiour to the Collapſed <hi>Angels</hi> or reiected <hi>Iſraelites?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My beloued, I muſt ingeniouſly acknowledge with the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie, Puer ſum, et neſcio loqui,</hi> I am <note place="margin">Ieremy 1. 6.</note> but a child and know not how to ſpeake: fitter like an Auditour to ſit at <hi>Gamaliels feete,</hi> then like a Doctor in <hi>Moſes chaire.</hi> Yet ſeeing the <note place="margin">Acts 22. 3. Matt. 23. 2.</note> Lord hath called mee to <hi>this place,</hi> and put his word into my mouth: I beſeech you ſuffer with all patience and reuerent attention, a word or two of premonition and exhortation. It may pleaſe God ſo to magnifie his ſtrength in my weakneſſe, as to make the wordes which hee hath taught mee effectually powerfull for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177608:49"/> of your liues, and conſe quently for the euerlaſting ſaluation of your Soules and Bodies.</p>
            <p>Shall euery tree not bringing forth good fruit bee hewen downe and caſt <note place="margin">1 Clergy</note> into the fire? O lay this vnto heart with mee yee <hi>Chariots and horſemen of Iſrael,</hi> yee that are of the <hi>houſe of Aaron</hi> and the <hi>Tribe of Leui,</hi> my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued fellow-labourers in the worke of the <hi>Miniſterie.</hi> Let vs conſider that the Lord hath committed vnto vs the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of his <hi>Word,</hi> that <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1. 1. Pet. 1. 23.</note> moſt <hi>precious and immortall ſeede</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſt may be conceiued in vs, and we become <hi>ſpirituall Fathers</hi> of many <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Children</hi> in Chriſt. O then let euery one of vs in the feare of God, according to the Talent wherwith we are entruſted, ſo labour in the Word to be found <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpenſers</hi> of the Word, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eding the flocke of Chriſt concredited to our charge with ſauory food <hi>in ſeaſon, &amp; out of ſeaſon,</hi> that we may become <hi>fruitfull</hi> in <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 2.</note> begetting children vnto Chriſt for the enlarging of his Kingdome. Let vs remember that the <hi>Church</hi> is Gods <hi>vineyard,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> his <hi>plants,</hi> and we the <hi>Miniſters</hi> his <hi>hired ſeruants,</hi> to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177608:50"/> labour in his <hi>vineyard</hi> that it may yeeld forth <hi>fruit</hi> vnto the Lord. And though <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> may haue a back-friend in <hi>Herods</hi> court, yet let vs not be put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or diſcourag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, but boldly with a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art ſtrike with the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> at the head of that Serpent <hi>Sinne,</hi> in whomſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer we ſee it: remembring that wee are <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 20.</note> One who is able to maintaine his cauſe euen againſt the <hi>Deuill</hi> himſelfe. But aboue all, let vs labour to put life into our labours, by <hi>bringing forth</hi> the <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>good liuing,</hi> that ſo wee may the better winne our people to entertaine the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cere Profeſsion of the Truth, and ſaue our owne Soules at the day of the Lord <hi>Jeſus.</hi> For as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> moſt <note place="margin">Serm de Sancto Benedicto Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</note> ſweetly, <hi>Sermo vivus &amp; efficax Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris eſt, plurimum faciens ſuadibile quod dicitur, dum monſtrat factibile quod ſuadetur:</hi> Wee ſhall eaſily perſwade the people to practiſe what we preach, when what wee preach, we practiſe. In a word, let vs remember, that as there it a <hi>Vae mihi ſi non euangeliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vero,</hi> a woe vnto the Miniſter if hee doe not labour in the Goſpell: ſo there is a <hi>vae mihi ſi non bene vixero,</hi> a woe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177608:50"/> vnto the Miniſter if he doe not liue according to the Goſpell: for <hi>euery Tree</hi> that bringeth not forth <hi>good fruite,</hi> the fruite of <hi>good liuing</hi> ſhall bee <hi>hewne downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place thinke vpon this yee People of <hi>this place,</hi> of this <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Laytie.</note> of this <hi>Land.</hi> Sure I am, there is no Nation vnder the Celeſtiall Poles, prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſsing the faith of Chriſt ouer which the Lord hath placed ſo <hi>Learned,</hi> ſo <hi>Laborious,</hi> ſo <hi>Religious</hi> a <hi>Clergy</hi> as ouer <hi>This.</hi> Conſider how in it yee are bleſt of God, that ſo yee may bleſſe God when yee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it: Bleſſe God? but how! why, bleſſe him in Sacrificing vnto him the <hi>Calues of your lippes: Bleſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſca 14. 2.</note> 
               <hi>him</hi> in conſecrating vnto him the ſhort remnant and <hi>remainder of your liues: Bleſſe him</hi> in a reuerend eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his <hi>holy Ordinances:</hi> In a word, <hi>Bleſſe him</hi> in your ſingular loue vnto thoſe that are ouer you in the <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 12, 13.</note> Lord, that are <hi>dispenſers</hi> of his <hi>ſacred myſteries:</hi> leaſt yee bee <hi>hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doe yee not ſo? I would to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177608:51"/> God I could paſſe by you concerning theſe particulars, eſpecially the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> without apprehending any iuſt cauſe for your generall reprehenſion. It is a Sore I no more but touched, but named before, intending in this place to handle it more at large, and to apply vnto it a corroding Plaiſter, if it were poſsible, to draw away the malignant qualitie wherewith it is ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted: that it is euen ſwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne vp as high as Heauen, to the pulling downe (as is iuſtly to bee feared) vpon this Land, a ſudden <hi>Babel</hi> of confuſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſpeedy reformation.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but there are <hi>ſome Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 15.</note> amongſt vs that would <hi>plucke out euen their owne eyes,</hi> to doe <hi>Paul</hi> good. That there is <hi>ſome Zareptan,</hi> that <note place="margin">1 Kings 17.</note> would euen hazard the haſtening her owne <hi>hunger-ſtaruing</hi> to communicate vnto <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> neceſsities: for whoſe ſakes, I am perſwaded, the Lord hath been many wayes gracious vnto this <hi>Land,</hi> and ſuſpended the infliction of his fearefull iudgements which for our ſinnes wee haue long ſince iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. But alas, all theſe <hi>Some,</hi> theſe <hi>Galathians,</hi> theſe <hi>Zareptans</hi> are but a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177608:51"/> 
               <hi>ſmall Summe,</hi> ſcarce to be called a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in reſpect of thoſe that are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily affected. For as it was the ſin of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> with which he is branded vnto <note place="margin">1 Kings 12. 3.</note> poſteritie by the Spirit of God, that he made <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>loweſt</hi> and <hi>baſeſt</hi> of the <hi>People:</hi> ſo it is a ſinne may bee ſeene and read in <hi>great characters.</hi> vpon the <hi>foreheads</hi> of moſt in this <hi>Land,</hi> that they make <hi>Prieſts</hi> the loweſt and baſeſt of <hi>People:</hi> the loweſt, by depriuing them of their <hi>allotted Maintenance;</hi> the baſeſt, by proſecuting them with all <hi>vnreuerence.</hi> Not to ſpeak of the <hi>former,</hi> and <hi>therin</hi> of thoſe violent, maleuolent, vnchriſtian-like courſes wherein they are very frequent, and fruitfull for the diſpoyling, and robbing vs of thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues God out of his holy wiſcome hath ſet apart, and conſecrated for the maintenance of thoſe that miniſter and ſerue at his <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar,</hi> that ſo they might make the <hi>Leuites</hi> to ſtoope vnto them, and hang vpon their ſleeues like <hi>beggers</hi> for their <hi>Almes</hi> and <hi>voluntary contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> How vnreaſonably do they load the Prophets of the Lord with all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries &amp; indignities their deuiliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice can inuent? The ſacred title of our
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177608:52"/> 
               <hi>thrice honourable Function</hi> is but a terme of diſgrace in the mouths of theſe <hi>ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Iſmaels,</hi> whoſe malignant ſpleene is ſuch, that they will not ſtick to ſtrike at vs with the ſword of their virulent tongues, euen in the <hi>face of the world,</hi> as we walke in the open ſtreets. Nay, ſuch is the height of their impudency, that they will not forb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are to offer violence vnto the honour of our Calling, euen <hi>before Gods own face,</hi> euen in the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> it ſelfe, which hath alwayes bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a place of priuiledge, as if they would out-beard &amp; out-braue almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God himſelfe. Is it poſsible ſuch a <hi>high-handed diſrespect</hi> and contempt ſhould raigne where the Goſpell of Chriſt is ſo plentifully, and ſo ſincerely preached?</p>
            <p>But I doe the leſſe maruell at it, when I call to mind the baſe vſage wherwith the <hi>Son of God,</hi> that <hi>High Prieſt for euer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 6. 20.</note> 
               <hi>after the Order of Melchiſedeck,</hi> our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in the dayes of the fleſh: <hi>He was in the world</hi> (ſaith the beloued Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt) <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 10. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not. He came vnto his owne, and his owne receiued him not.</hi> Nay,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177608:52"/> they did not onely not receiue him, but did, as ye may read at large in the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of his life,</hi> proſecute and perſecute him with a world of indignities, euen <hi>vnto the death.</hi> Now the <hi>Diſciple is not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 10. 24, 25</note> 
               <hi>aboue his Maſter, nor the ſeruant aboue his Lord. It is enough</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>for the diſciple to be as his maſter is, and the ſeruant as his Lord. If they haue called the maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more them of his houſhold?</hi> Our Lord hath drunke vnto vs out of this <hi>bittercup,</hi> and we muſt reſolue to <hi>pledge him round.</hi> O thrice happy we, if wee could ſo apprehend it, that he is pleaſed to accept vs into his ſufferings. For <hi>if we ſuffer with Chriſt, we may bee aſſured</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall alſo raigne with Chriſt.</hi> But vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy all thoſe whoſe delight to grieue our ſpirits by their diſreſpectiue cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and vnconſcionable courſes, ſhall make vs to be called <hi>Great</hi> in the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>heauen:</hi> yea, thrice vnhappy and accurſed, if they breake not off this their ſinfulneſſe by a more <hi>ſanctified</hi> and <hi>conſcionable courſe of life.</hi> We are indeed but weake <hi>Earthen veſſels,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <note place="margin">2 Cor. 47.</note> ſtileth vs. We are ſinfull men, men full of ſinne, and therin not vnlike your
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177608:53"/> ſelues: let him that is among you with out ſinne caſt the firſt ſtone at vs. Yet <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 7.</note> conſider that we are your <hi>Spirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 15. Reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> that wee are the <hi>Angels of God,</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadours for Chriſt.</hi> If we be <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5, 20.</note> your <hi>Fathers,</hi> where is our <hi>honour?</hi> What though <hi>Eliſha</hi> be bald? ſhall the children of <hi>Bethel</hi> cal him Baldpate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? No, two Beares come out of <note place="margin">2 Kin. 2. 22, 23.</note> the Forreſt, and tare them in pieces. What though <hi>Noah</hi> be drunken? ſhall his ſonne <hi>Ham</hi> mocke and deride him without a curſe? No, <hi>Canaan is curſed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 9. 25.</note> 
               <hi>a ſeruant of ſeruants ſhall hee bee vnto his brethren.</hi> If we be <hi>Angels</hi> of God and <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> for Chriſt, where is that <hi>homage</hi> and <hi>reuerence</hi> you owe vnto vs in the name of our Lord and Maſter? Will an earthly Prince, which is but a piece of clay, take to heart as done to himſelfe, whatſoeuer indignitie is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto his <hi>Ambaſſadours?</hi> And will not Almightie God be ſenſible of that diſhonour which is daily done vnto his <hi>Ambaſſadours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue heard credibly related, how ſuperciliouſly and contemptuouſly the <hi>Palſgraues Countrey</hi> hath looked vpon their <hi>Clergie.</hi> In what caſe that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:177608:53"/> now ſtandeth, I ſuppoſe the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Chriſtian Region is not ignorant. I will not preſume peremptorily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine that this one ſinne hath been the procuring cauſe of ſo fearefull a Iudgement. Thus much I am ſure of, that the <hi>contempt</hi> of the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of <note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on. 36 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> God coſt <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a <hi>deſolation.</hi> God is ſo tender ouer his Prophets, that he will not haue them ſo much as toucht: hee hath reprooued euen <hi>Kings</hi> for their ſakes. So ſenſibly he is affected with the wrongs they ſuſtaine, that hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them as done <hi>to Himſelfe.</hi> Do ye rob them of their <hi>Tythes? Ye haue robbed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Malac 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>me,</hi> ſaith the Lord. Doe ye <hi>neglect</hi> and <hi>despiſe</hi> them? <hi>Ye deſpiſe me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <note place="margin">Luke 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and him that ſent mee,</hi> euen God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And wil not the Lord reuenge <hi>theſe wrongs?</hi> Yea, hath hee not already in ſome meaſure puniſhed this land for them? Haue not the <hi>Coales</hi> your Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers haue ſtolne from Gods <hi>altar,</hi> ſet their <hi>neaſts on fire,</hi> brought a curſe vpon their ſubſtance, that it hath not thriued vnto a <hi>third generation?</hi> yea, whilſt they and you haue <hi>denyed</hi> God his <hi>Tenth part,</hi> hath not God <hi>taken away</hi> your <hi>Nine parts,</hi> and giuen you onely a <hi>Tenth?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177608:54"/>
            <p>Againe, hath not the Lord taken vnto himſelfe many <hi>conſcionable</hi> and <hi>painefull Miniſters,</hi> which according to the courſe of nature might haue liued long, to haue bin <hi>worthy Inſtruments</hi> for <hi>your euerlaſting good,</hi> becauſe ye haue ſo <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued</hi> them, and ſet ſo <hi>low an eſtimate</hi> vpon them? But alas, my Beloued, theſe are but <hi>flea bitings</hi> if compared to the <hi>remoouing</hi> of our <hi>Candleſticke</hi> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. 5.</note> vs: and is it not iuſtly to bee feared, that he hath euen at this preſent ſome ſuch work in hand? I pray God he hath not. But ſay he doe continue the <hi>light of his Goſpel</hi> amongſt vs: yet what benefit can accrue vnto vs by <hi>this light,</hi> if we be <hi>taken from it,</hi> and <hi>caſt into vtter darkneſſe?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his God can doe, and will doe, if wee doe not bring forth better fruit: for <hi>euery tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, ſhall bee hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> O conſider of this, all yee whoſe <hi>greateſt glory</hi> is to bee the <hi>ſcourge</hi> of the <hi>Clergie;</hi> leſt that <hi>High Prieſt</hi> Chriſt Ieſus take you in hand, and ye be made to howle eternally in <hi>Hell,</hi> for contemning his Subſtitutes, his <hi>low Prieſtes</hi> here on earth. Let the Word of the Lord, and the Miniſters
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177608:54"/> therof be <hi>precious in your ſight,</hi> that you &amp; your poſterity may be <hi>precious in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> Haue thoſe that are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you in the Lord, &amp; labour amongſt you in ſingular loue, if not for their owne ſakes, yet for their Maſters ſake, and for their workes ſake, conſidering how like Candles they conſume and waſte themſelues away to light you in the way vnto perpetual happines. Giue vnto them double honour, and cut them not ſhort of their due <hi>reuerence</hi> &amp; <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> leſt the Lord in his fury cut you off from the ſtate of mercy, leſt ye be <hi>hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue, I ſuppoſe, not a little exceeded your <hi>expectation,</hi> I am ſure, my firſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> in giuing ſo much way vnto this laſt particulars <hi>extention:</hi> but the time I haue borrowed of you in it, I will God willing, repay you to the full in the reſt that follow.</p>
            <p>Shal <hi>euery tree not bringing forth good fruit be hewen downe and caſt into the fire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Honourable Lord,</hi> I will giue you <note place="margin">3 The Lord Maior.</note> but a <hi>word,</hi> take heed God doe not one day giue you a <hi>blow.</hi> Hee hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> vnder his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> and hath put the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177608:55"/> 
               <hi>your hand.</hi> I would deſire you to take notice, that he hath alſo an <hi>Axe</hi> in <hi>his hand:</hi> therefore like a good tree <hi>bring forth good fruit</hi> in that place wherein he hath ſet you: be the <hi>Orphans father,</hi> and the <hi>Widowes husband:</hi> be of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and bee zealous for your great Lord and Maſter, your Maker the Lord of hoſts: protect and countenance the good; correct and cut down the bad, leſt the Lord <hi>hewe you downe and caſt you into Hell fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye <hi>Reuerend Iudges</hi> of the Land, and <note place="margin">4 Iudges and Lawyers.</note> all ye that trauell in the <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> remember there is a dreadfull <hi>Judge</hi> aboue you, euen the <hi>Lord</hi> of Heauen and Earth, who will one day call all of you to a <hi>ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> for all your courſes. Therefore like good trees bring forth <hi>good fruite</hi> in your ſeuerall places, as you will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it at the <hi>Barre</hi> of his <hi>Tribunal.</hi> Let neither the <hi>feare of greatnes,</hi> nor <hi>vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Mammon;</hi> let neither <hi>priuate ſpleene,</hi> nor <hi>particular affection</hi> ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with you, as to <hi>interturbe</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturne</hi> the courſe of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> but walk <hi>vprightly</hi> and <hi>conſcionably,</hi> as hauing the <hi>feare of God</hi> before your eyes, <hi>leſt he hew</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:177608:55"/> 
               <hi>you downe and caſt you into hell fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All ye that exerciſe your ſelues in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> 
               <note place="margin">5 Tradeſmen.</note> 
               <hi>commerce,</hi> come hither and conſider what I ſhall ſay vnto you. What will it aduantage you to bee Lords ouer the <hi>whole world,</hi> &amp; to looſe <hi>your owne ſoules?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 25.</note> Therefore ſo Sell and Buy, and Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter, that ye make not <hi>ſhipwracke</hi> of a <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> &amp; looſe the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into your Bargaines: that is, deale honeſtly and ſincerely with al men, as it becommeth the <hi>Seruants of Chriſt:</hi> and doe not go about cunningly to intrap any with termes of <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> and to cheat them with <hi>falſe Wares, Meaſures,</hi> and <hi>Weights:</hi> for theſe things are <hi>an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination</hi> vnto the Lord. But aboue all things, take heed of that moſt frequent and moſt fearefull cuſtome of <hi>ſwearing worth</hi> and <hi>credit</hi> into your <hi>Commodities;</hi> leſt while ye labour to make them mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable, and good penny-worths with man: yee looſe your credit and your penny, that is, your <hi>Crowne of Glory</hi> with God. Thinke vpon it, for beleeue it the time will come, when the Lord ſhall <hi>weigh you</hi> in his <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9, 25.</note> as he did <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> and ſhall, if he find you <hi>too light,</hi> ſeperate you from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:177608:56"/> the Kingdome of Heauen as farre as the <hi>Eaſt</hi> is from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and the <hi>North</hi> from the <hi>South:</hi> for <hi>euery Tree that bringeth not forth good fruite, ſhall bee hewen downe and caſt into the Fre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e notice of this all ye, whom the Lord hath linked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <note place="margin">6 Maried fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke.</note> in <hi>Holy and Honourable Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony:</hi> that ſo yee may bring forth fruit beſeeming ſo holy and ſo honourable an eſtate. Make conſcience of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thoſe ſeuerall Offices and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects God in his Sacred Word requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of you one towards another. Bee Carefull Religiouſly and Conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obſerue and pay thoſe <hi>Solemne vowes</hi> yee made before God and Men at the <hi>Solemnization</hi> of your <hi>Nuptialls.</hi> More particularly and principa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 24.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> hath made you <hi>One</hi> of <hi>Two,</hi> ſuffer not the <hi>Diuel</hi> to make you <hi>Two</hi> of <hi>One:</hi> but liue <hi>peaceably, diſcreetly,</hi> and <hi>loyally</hi> together: nouriſh mutuall affection, and <hi>poſſeſſe your veſſels,</hi> that <note place="margin">1. Theſſ 4. 4.</note> is, your bodies <hi>in holineſſe and honour:</hi> and keepe your ſelues one to another <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b 13. 4</note> as <hi>vndefiled members</hi> of Chriſts Body, free from <hi>luſting after ſtrange fleſh,</hi> leaſt yee bee hewen downe <hi>and caſt into the Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:177608:56"/>
            <p>Againe, ſhall euery Tree not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth good fruit be hewen downe and caſt into the fire?</p>
            <p>Conſider this all yee whom the Lord hath bleſſed with the <hi>fruite</hi> of the <hi>Wombe,</hi> leaſt this <hi>temporall bleſsing</hi> proue <note place="margin">7 Parents.</note> your <hi>eternall bane.</hi> Thinke it not enough that yee bring forth children <hi>into the world,</hi> and prouide for them an <hi>earthly inheritance:</hi> vnleſſe yee alſo bring them vp <hi>vnto the Lord,</hi> and ſo fit them for the <hi>Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> Alaſſe, what is their <hi>firſt generation</hi> more then <hi>their Corruption?</hi> for they are <hi>ſhaped in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51 5.</note> 
               <hi>and conceiued in ſinne:</hi> and ſo poore Infants, <hi>Damnati antequam nati,</hi> they are damned before their mothers are deliuered: and being ſo, what is your <hi>Temporall prouiſion</hi> vnto them, though neuer ſo plentifull: if after their ioy in <hi>this World</hi> (if they know any) they be ſo farre from knowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the <hi>next,</hi> that on the contrary they lye howling in Hell flames for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? If therefore you truely loue your Children, for <hi>their ſakes</hi> vndertake a <hi>ſecond labour,</hi> and bring forth this good fruite of your <hi>Fatherly loue</hi> towards them, once more <hi>trauell in paine of them,</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:177608:57"/> but as <hi>Paul</hi> did of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> till <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> be <hi>formed</hi> in <hi>them:</hi> labour that they may be <hi>begotten a new in Chriſt by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the immortall ſeede of the Word,</hi> and bee made heyres of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Let it be your care, whatſoeuer it coſt, to haue them brought vp euen from their <hi>Child-hood in the feare of God.</hi> That when they leaue this world, they may attaine vnto the Land of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, there to raigne with Chriſt world without end. And if you will not doe thus much for <hi>their ſakes,</hi> at leaſt doe it for your <hi>owne ſakes.</hi> For know, to bring forth this good fruit of true fatherly affection, to bee carefull for the <hi>Spirituall well-fare</hi> of your Children, and to promote and further it to the vtmoſt of your power, is a <hi>dutie</hi> God ſtrictly inioyneth. And if through <hi>neglect hereof</hi> your Children <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>rebell</hi> againſt God, he will require their <hi>blood at your hands.</hi> For as God doth viſite the ſinnes of the Fathers vpon the Children: So he doth viſite the ſinns of the Children vpon the Fathers. For an inſtance remember Old <hi>Eli:</hi> when his <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnes</hi> treſpaſſed againſt God, He did not ſharpely reprooue and correct them: but ſuffered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to run on in their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177608:57"/> Sins: &amp; this was his ruine: In a word, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the Iudge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here threatned in my Text, &amp; be moued thereby to bring forth the good fruite of true Fatherly affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: inſtruct your Children in the feare of the Lord: reproue &amp; correct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they offend the Lord: <hi>leaſt the Lord hew you downe and caſt you into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner yee <hi>Children,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Rocke out of which yee <note place="margin">8 Children.</note> were <hi>hewen,</hi> the <hi>Stocke</hi> whereof yee are <hi>ſtemmes:</hi> your <hi>Parents</hi> from whom, next vnder God, yee haue receiued your <hi>naturall beeing.</hi> Oh wound not their tender hearts with your vntoward carriage and rebellious courſes, the only courſe to <hi>accelerate</hi> and haſten their <hi>heads</hi> to the <hi>graue:</hi> but like <hi>good Children,</hi> bring forth the good fruit of <hi>filiall feare</hi> and <hi>affection,</hi> that yee may <hi>exhilarate</hi> &amp; reioyce their <hi>Soules</hi> to the <hi>prolonging</hi> of their dayes. Reuerence them <hi>inwardly</hi> in your <hi>hearts,</hi> &amp; <hi>outward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</hi> in your <hi>Behauiour:</hi> yeeld vnto them all <hi>dutifull obedience</hi> in the Lord, leaſt ye pluck <hi>their Curſe</hi> vpon your heads, and the Lord hearing it, <hi>hew you downe &amp; caſt you into the fire.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">9 Maſters of families.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yee that haue the care of Seruants
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177608:58"/> committed to your charge, bring forth the Good fruite of <hi>Good Maſters</hi> in your ſeuerall Families: doe vnto your Seruants that which is <hi>iuſt and equall,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 1.</note> knowing that yee <hi>alſo haue a Maſter in Heauen.</hi> Command them not but in <hi>the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>louingly.</hi> Allow them a <hi>befitting competency,</hi> be it in matter of ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment for the Backe, or aliment for the Belly; and doe not with-hold their <hi>wages</hi> from them. But aboue all, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the knowledge and feare of God, as well by your examples, as precepts: and allow not their <hi>profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Lords <hi>Sabaths</hi> the leaſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuence:</hi> Leaſt the Lord <hi>hew you downe and caſt you into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yee that are <hi>Seruants,</hi> ſerue your <note place="margin">10 Seruants.</note> Maſters <hi>faithfully</hi> both in <hi>word</hi> and <hi>deede:</hi> and obſerue them with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue reuerence, and ſubmit your ſelues vnto them to obey them in the Lord, <hi>leaſt the Lord hew downe you alſo, and caſt you into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, to drawe towards a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, giue me leaue to drawe out an <hi>Eare</hi> or two of the <hi>Corne</hi> we haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>inn'd:</hi> for I feare growing too vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous and large, in particularizing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:177608:58"/> farther. Yee haue heard how <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>bountifull</hi> a God the Lord hath vowed to ſhew himſelfe vnto all thoſe that ſubmit themſelues <hi>vnto his lawes,</hi> and labour to ſerue him faithfully in <hi>bringing forth good fruite:</hi> in leading a holy and religious courſe of life: that he will reward and crowne their holy endeauours with an <hi>eternall weight of Glory</hi> in the kingdome of Heauen. Yee haue likewiſe heard how <hi>ſeuere</hi> and <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible</hi> a Iudge hee will reueale himſelfe vnto all ſuch as runne <hi>diſobedient</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious courſes,</hi> that <hi>hee will wound the hayrie Scalpe of euery one that goeth on in his wickedneſſe:</hi> yea, that hee will <hi>hew downe</hi> and <hi>caſt into the fire</hi> euery Tree not bringing forth <hi>good fruite.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſweete bleſsings of <hi>Gerizim,</hi> the louing mercies of God cannot worke vpon our rebellious hearts, to reclaime vs from our wicked wayes: let the bitter curſings of <hi>Eball,</hi> the dreadfull terrours of the Law make vs feare to offend: leaſt the Lord in his wrath deliuer vs vp vnto a <hi>reprobate minde,</hi> and in that fearefull eſtate <hi>hew vs downe:</hi> that is, by a violent Death rent our Soules and Bodies a ſunder:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177608:59"/> &amp; <hi>caſt vs</hi> both ſoule &amp; body <hi>into the fire,</hi> to be intollerably &amp; eternally tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the flames of Hel. My beloued, as God is <hi>Iealous</hi> of, ſo he is <hi>Zealous</hi> for his glory: if he be not glorified <hi>a nobis,</hi> of vs <hi>by our conuerſion:</hi> he will be glorified <hi>de nobis</hi> vpon vs, <hi>by our confuſion:</hi> if we do not turne <hi>vnto him,</hi> he wil turne vs <hi>into Hell:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or it is a concluſion ſo ratified, as neuer to bee repealed: that <hi>Euery one</hi> whether <hi>Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, bond</hi> or <hi>free, high</hi> or <hi>low, rich</hi> or <hi>poore: Euery tree not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth good fruit, ſhall be hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> O then, let <hi>euery one</hi> of vs make a diligent ſearch into his <hi>owne boſome,</hi> &amp; iudge <hi>himſelfe,</hi> leaſt he be iudged of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Let vs diſſect &amp; rip vp that <hi>body of ſinne</hi> which is <hi>within vs;</hi> not only that <hi>Naturall corruption,</hi> which we haue all alike ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſsiuely receiued from our firſt Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, but alſo thoſe <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal tranſgreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> which euery man hath made himſelfe guilty of, more or leſſe. Then hauing faithfully laid open our ſinfulnes, let vs look on it with a <hi>loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye</hi> &amp; a <hi>lamenting heart:</hi> vnfeinedly deploring the time wherein to our <hi>iuſt damnation,</hi> had we our deſerts, we haue not only brought forth <hi>no fruit,</hi> but alſo
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177608:59"/> 
               <hi>naughty fruit,</hi> fruite curſed &amp; abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: &amp; herein, not only diſhonored God <hi>our ſelues:</hi> but alſo, to our <hi>further damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> drawn <hi>others</hi> to doe the like by our <hi>lewd examples:</hi> for which, let vs go with <hi>faith</hi> in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt to the throne of <hi>Grace,</hi> imploring <hi>mercy</hi> at the hands of our heauenly <hi>Father,</hi> who is ready &amp; willing to imbrace with the armes of his mercy, al ſuch petitioning him for grace in <hi>the Name of his Sonne:</hi> &amp; let vs for the <hi>time following,</hi> entertain this ſetled reſolution into our hearts, faithfully to labor in the <hi>reformation</hi> of all thoſe faults we lament: And which is the <hi>conſummation &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of our <hi>repentance,</hi> let vs crowne our holy <hi>reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> by putting them into <hi>action:</hi> by <hi>bringing forth fruit worthy amendment of life,</hi> as it is in the verſe before my Text, or as it is here in my Text, by <hi>bringing forth good fruit,</hi> by leading in our ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places &amp; callings a right holy &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious courſe of life. For it is not a bare entertainement of better courſes into our thoughts, of <hi>dead,</hi> of <hi>naked purpoſes:</hi> nor an <hi>outſide of Religion,</hi> an outward conformity to the ſeruice of God, will preſerue vs from the wrath to come:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177608:60"/> the <hi>former</hi> being but a bringing forth of <hi>good leaues,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> but of <hi>good flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> or if of <hi>fruit,</hi> but of ſuch as is <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>counterfeit:</hi> No, wee muſt either bring forth <hi>good fruit,</hi> that is, as ye haue heard, <hi>Fruit</hi> not onely <hi>outwardly beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and <hi>good</hi> in the eye of man, but alſo <hi>inwardly good and ſound</hi> in the ſight of God, or we muſt vndergoe the wrath of God be <hi>hewen down, and caſt into the fire.</hi> Such fruit muſt euery Tree bring forth, and that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Properanter,</hi> preſently.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Abundanter,</hi> plentifully.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Perſeueranter,</hi> perſeuerantly.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, we muſt bring forth good fruit <note place="margin">VVe muſt bring foorth good fruit 1. Preſently.</note> 
               <hi>properanter,</hi> preſently; it is a taske wee muſt take in hand <hi>out of hand:</hi> as much is implied in the letter of my text, <hi>Euery tree,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>bringing</hi> forth good fruit, that is, <hi>Now, preſently</hi> (for it is a word of the <hi>preſent tenſe,</hi> and doth vrge a <hi>preſent taske)</hi> ſhal be <hi>hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> This <hi>Speed</hi> is emphatically preſſed in the firſt words of my text, <hi>Now is the axe laid vnto the root of the trees;</hi> as if the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> had more largely deliuered himſelfe thus: It is <hi>no delaying</hi> the time of your turning vnto God: he
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177608:60"/> hath taried your leaſure ſo long, that he is reſolued to attend you no longer: therefore looke to your ſelues, God wil now be but <hi>a word</hi> and <hi>a blow:</hi> for he hath already taken his <hi>Axe,</hi> the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death, <hi>into his hand:</hi> yea he hath <hi>already lifted vp his arme</hi> to ſtrike: nay more, he hath ſo farre ſet forward his blow, that he hath euen <hi>laid</hi> his <hi>Axe to the root of the trees,</hi> reſolutely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to make his blow, to hew you downe <hi>out of hand,</hi> and caſt you into the fire, if ye do not <hi>preſently repent,</hi> &amp; bring foorth fruite worthy amendment of life. O then, my beloued, I beſeech you let vs conſider, that <hi>now onely</hi> is the time of making or marring our fortunes for euer. Alas, what is our life but a blaſt? <hi>Spiraemus, expiramus:</hi> we breath, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly our breath is gone. So it is, that no man liuing can aſſure vnto himſelfe the leaſt moment of time beyond that which he doth at the very inſtant inioy. Indeed the <hi>Deuill,</hi> to lead vs on in our ſinnes, would perſwade vs, that <hi>Nature</hi> hath ſealed vnto vs a <hi>long Leaſe</hi> of our liues; and that we need not as yet trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our heads with repentance; there will be time enough for that <hi>hereafter.</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:177608:61"/> But the truth is, we hold this <hi>fading breath</hi> but as Gods <hi>Tenants at will.</hi> Hee may and will, if it pleaſe him, without the <hi>leaſt warning</hi> take it away from vs. But ſuppoſe we may liue long, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent time enough hereafter, for that <hi>poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia vera nunquam ſera,</hi> True repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitentia ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o vera.</note> is neuer too late: yet are we ſure we can repent when wee pleaſe? No, <hi>True repentance</hi> is the <hi>gift of God,</hi> and it is iuſt with him to <hi>deny it</hi> that man at his death, which hath ſo <hi>careleſſely negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it</hi> throughout the whole courſe of his life.</p>
            <p>So that in a word, <hi>in mora</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is but a folly, yea extreame madneſſe to dally and delay the time of our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, conſidering the <hi>imminent wrath</hi> of God, and our own <hi>frailty.</hi> Sure I am, <hi>As the tree falleth,</hi> ſo <hi>it lyeth;</hi> as <hi>Death lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs,</hi> ſo <hi>Iudgement findeth vs.</hi> Let vs therfore euen <hi>Now,</hi> whilſt it is called <hi>to day,</hi> begin to worke out our ſaluation with <hi>feare</hi> &amp; <hi>trembling:</hi> When the <hi>night</hi> of Death <hi>commeth, no man can worke.</hi> Let vs <hi>Now,</hi> whileſt the <hi>acceptable little time</hi> of ſaluation laſteth, vnfainedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and call vpon God for mercy. Let it ſuffice that we haue ſpent <hi>the time paſt</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:177608:61"/> vpon the <hi>luſts of our own hearts,</hi> in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the <hi>corrupt fruit of the fleſh,</hi> in <hi>drunkenneſſe,</hi> in <hi>ſwearing,</hi> in <hi>profaneneſſe,</hi> in <hi>pride</hi> in <hi>vncleanneſſe,</hi> and the like: Let vs <hi>Now</hi> begin to awake out of ſin, and to walke in <hi>newneſſe of life:</hi> leſt the Lord do <hi>ſuddenly</hi> before we ſo much as dreame of it <hi>hew vs downe, and caſt vs into the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt bring forth good <note place="margin">2 Plentifully.</note> fruit <hi>abundanter,</hi> plentifully. It is the <hi>Encomium</hi> Chriſt giueth his <hi>Spouſe</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> that ſhee is an <hi>Orchard full of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cant. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſweet fruits.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> aſſirmeth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>their faith was publiſhed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 15. 14.</note> 
               <hi>throughout the whole world.</hi> &amp; Rom. 15. <hi>I am perſwaded,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ye are full of goodnes, &amp; filled with all knowledge;</hi> and of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> he affirmeth, that their <hi>faith did grow exceedingly, and their loue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>did generally abound.</hi> My beloued, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe &amp; the like teſtimonies of the Saints are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded for <hi>our imitation.</hi> The plain truth is, <hi>God</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not away with <hi>ſtarueling trees,</hi> ſuch <hi>Profeſſors</hi> as are <hi>Non-proficients.</hi> If therfore we mean to auoid the ſtroke of his <hi>axe,</hi> &amp; to be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>hel fire</hi> thretned in my text, we muſt like <hi>good trees thriue</hi> in our <hi>ſpiritual eſtate,</hi> we
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177608:62"/> muſt <hi>encreaſe and grow in grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> we muſt <hi>abound in euery good worke that may make vs perfit m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> we muſt bring forth good fruit <hi>pletifully</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good reaſon hath God to require it at our hands, conſidering the <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> 
               <note place="margin">VVe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth at our hands bringing forth of good fruit plentifully.</note> 
               <hi>coſt</hi> &amp; <hi>care</hi> he hath beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs to this end and purpoſe. For firſt as hath bin ſaid before, he hath bin plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to ſowe the <hi>pure ſeed</hi> of his <hi>Word</hi> in no place ſo plentifully as in this land in no place of this land ſo plentifully as in this Citie.</p>
            <p>Againe, that it might take deep root <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in our hearts to the bringing forth of good fruit plentifully in our liues, hee hath watered and refreſhed this his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance with infinite remarkable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of his ſingular ſauour, as it were with ſo many <note n="*" place="margin">Tum pater omnipoten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aether, &amp;c. <hi>Virg. 2. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>org.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſweete fructifying ſhowers</hi> from heauen: and to infuſe a quicken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng power into the ground of our hearts: he hath cauſed the Sunne of Peace, <note n="*" place="margin">Pax <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> derect v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tib. lib. 1. leg.</hi> 1. 3</note> 
               <hi>the Mother of Plenty,</hi> for theſe many yeares to ſhine vpon vs. In a word, what <hi>medicinall courſes</hi> hath hee neglected, which in the iudgement of man might conduce to the <hi>furthering</hi> of <hi>our fruitfulnes?</hi> He hath <hi>pared off</hi> our <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otous</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:177608:62"/> 
               <hi>Twigs,</hi> and <hi>lopped off</hi> our <hi>luxuriant Branches, ript vp</hi> our <hi>Rind, opened</hi> our <hi>Roots:</hi> that is, he hath ſcourged vs with <hi>ſundry kinds</hi> of <hi>Croſſes</hi> and <hi>Afflictions,</hi> that thereby hee might call vs backe from wandring abroad after the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching pleaſures of Sinne,</hi> to ſerue Him the <hi>onely true and euerliuing God,</hi> with a ſound and vpright heart in all <hi>holineſſe</hi> of life and conuerſation. All which layd together, wee haue no reaſon to thinke, that praying vnto God in the Church <hi>once a weeke,</hi> the hearing of a Sermon <hi>once a moneth,</hi> a ſtrict obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saboth <hi>once a quarter,</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Sacrament <hi>once in ſixe moneths,</hi> a Feaſting of the poore <hi>once a yeare</hi> will ſerue the turne. No, God will not be ſatisfied with ſuch a <hi>Barren</hi> and <hi>Dwarfling</hi> Obedience: he will not bee contented with the <hi>Gleanings of Harueſt,</hi> with <hi>heere a Bery,</hi> and <hi>there a Bery,</hi> as it was with the ſhaken <hi>Oliue Tree,</hi> Eſay 17. No, Euery tree muſt bring forth good fruit <hi>plentifully:</hi> for, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom ſoeuer much is giuen, of him</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 12. 48.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be much required,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>So that it doth ſtand vs euery one in hand accordingly to endeauour the <hi>reall</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:177608:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:177608:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:177608:64"/> 
               <hi>anſwering</hi> of Gods <hi>iuſt expectation,</hi> leſt in the day of his wrath, wee haue the <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eper ſhare</hi> in his <hi>juſt indignation.</hi> For <hi>Quantò maior gratia, tantò amplior po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteà</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quo clari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r lux <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> paenas mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nem ſibi ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rate. <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>peccantibus poena,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome.</hi> God will at the Laſt day pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion out the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of a ſinner according to the <hi>meanes of grace</hi> he hath afforded him in the time of his ſinning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At the worlds great Seſſions it ſhall go harder with <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> then with <hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sidon:</hi> it ſhall goe harder with <hi>Capernaum,</hi> then with <hi>Sodom:</hi> becauſe God did more abound in the <hi>meanes of grace</hi> to <hi>Chorazim, Bethſaida,</hi> and <hi>Capernaum,</hi> then to <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Sidon,</hi> and <hi>Sodome.</hi> Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath pleaſed God to deale ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally with vs in the <hi>meanes of Grace:</hi> let vs in the name of God endeauour in ſome proportion to anſwer his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>our meaſure of grace.</hi> Let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be <hi>full</hi> of the <hi>ſweet fruits</hi> of the Spirit: Let vs labour to bee <hi>ſtrong</hi> in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh) <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>With our Faith let vs ioyne Vertue; with Vertue, Knowledge; with Knowledge, Temperance; with Temperance, Patience; with Patience, Godlineſſe, with Godlineſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:177608:64"/> 
               <hi>Brotherly Kindneſſe; and with Brotherly Kindneſſe, Loue.</hi> In a word, let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to <hi>abound in euery good worke, that may make vs pleaſing and acceptable</hi> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God: let vs bring forth good fruit, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundanter,</hi> Plentifully.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, leſt all our labour <note place="margin">3 Perſeuerantly.</note> proue but in vaine, we muſt bring forth good fruit <hi>Perſeueranter,</hi> Perſeuerant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For to what purpoſe is it, if a <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier</hi> at the firſt onſet couragiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the <hi>Enemy:</hi> and before he hath obtained the victory, <hi>throw away his Armes?</hi> Or what doth it profit a <hi>Mariner</hi> to commit himſelfe to the Sea, and to enioy the benefit of a <hi>faire gale of Wind</hi> euen vnto his deſired <hi>Ports mouth:</hi> if then the wind doe turne, and ſo <hi>turne him backe againe</hi> before hee can thruſt into the Port? Happily <hi>thou haſt beene juſt, and haſt done that which is lawfull and right,</hi> as it is in <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18. 5. <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.</note> More particularly, as the Prophet there expreſſeth himſelfe, <hi>Thou haſt not eaten vpon the Moun aines, nor lift vp thine eyes vnto Idols, nor defiled thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wife, nor oppreſſed any, but haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to thy Debtour his Pledge: thou haſt ſpoyled none by violence; thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:177608:65"/> 
               <hi>thy Bread to the Hungry, and couered the Naked with a Garment; thou haſt not giuen forth vpon Vſury, neither taken any Increaſe: thou haſt withdrawen thy hand from iniquitie, &amp; executed true Judgement betweene man and man: thou haſt walked in Gods Statutes, and kept his Iudgements to deale truely.</hi> Thus farre haſt thou gone, and in theſe good courſes thou haſt continued a long time, and in ſo doing haſt done well: But tell mee, what will all this thy righteouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile thee, if afterward thou ſhalt <hi>fall away</hi> from God, and <hi>intangle thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>in the filthineſſe of the world, like the Dog that returneth to his owne vomit, and the Sow that is waſhed, to her wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the myre? If the righteous turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.</note> 
               <hi>from his righteouſneſse, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iniquitie, ſhall hee liue?</hi> ſaith the Lord. No, <hi>All his righteouſneſſe that he hath done, ſhall not bee mentioned: In his trespaſſe that hee hath trespaſsed, and in his ſinne that hee hath ſinned, in them ſhall hee dye.</hi> Ezek. 18. Yea, <hi>It had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him neuer to haue acknowledged the way of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> (as the Apoſtle <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> ſpeaketh) <hi>then after hee hath knowne it, to turne from the holy Commandement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:177608:65"/> vnto him: <hi>For the latter end of that man, is worſe then the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore thou wouldſt make ſure worke for the good of thy Soule, and ſtore vp comfort for thy ſelfe againſt the day of death, and that great day of wrath: then thou muſt not relye vpon thy former righteouſneſſe, as the <hi>Rich man</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> did vpon the ſtore he <note place="margin">Luke 12. 19.</note> had treaſured vp in his Barnes: and ſay, <hi>Soule take thine eaſe,</hi> and freely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thy ſelfe hence-forward in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of ſinne; <hi>for thou haſt already</hi> brought forth good fruit plentifully, which will ſerue thee for many yeares. No, thou muſt bring forth good fruite <hi>Perſeuerantly:</hi> for it is not here ſaid, euery tree, <hi>Quae non fecit,</hi> which hath not brought forth good fruit: but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tree <hi>non faciens,</hi> not bringing forth good fruit ſhall be hewen downe and caſt into the fire: So that <hi>feciſſe non ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit,</hi> it ſufficeth not formerly to haue brought forth good fruit, vnleſſe thou continue in ſo doeing <hi>perſeuerantly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>putting his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 62.</note> 
               <hi>hand to the Plough, and looking backe, is fit for the Kingdome of Heauen. Sola per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerantia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernardus.</note> 
               <hi>ſingularis ſummi regis eſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:177608:66"/> (ſaith a Father) <hi>ea enim ſola eſt haeres regn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Coelorum:</hi> Perſeuerance is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Daughter of the King of Heauen, for ſhe only is H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire to the Kingdome of Heauen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to his Diſciples, <hi>Qui perſeuerauerit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 24. 13</note> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nueth to the end ſhall bee ſaued: and to the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Be thou faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee a Crowne of Life.</hi> And vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe termes doth <hi>Saint Paul</hi> aſſure himſelfe, and euery faithfull Chriſtian a Crowne of righteouſneſſe: <hi>I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>courſe; I haue kept the faith. Hence forth is laid vp for me the Crowne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee at that day: and not to mee only, but vnto all them alſo that loue that his appearing.</hi> The <hi>abſolute neceſsity</hi> of this Perſeuerance for all ſuch as expect the Happineſſe of a better life, hath ſo deepely, ſunke into the thoughts of Gods Children in all ages, that they haue conſtantly reſolued to ſuffer the <hi>bittereſt torments</hi> the pregnant malice of the Diuell and his Factors could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon them; rather then to looſe the bleſſed hope of their <hi>Heauenly inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:177608:66"/> If therefore wee reſpect our Future Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pineſſe, let vs not bee like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> plant <hi>Epheme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> which doth ſpring and flouriſh, and fade <hi>in a day:</hi> but as the <hi>Oliue tree</hi> flouriſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th and fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>all the yeare long.</hi> ſo let vs <hi>continue</hi> in bringing forth good fruit <hi>perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly.</hi> To be ſhort, the way to Heauen though it be <hi>Narrow</hi> yet it is <hi>Long:</hi> and our life at the <hi>Longeſt</hi> but <hi>Short.</hi> Let vs therefore, that we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter compaſſe ſo great a Iourney, get vp betimes out of our beds of Sinne, euen in the morning of our age, at the firſt houre of the day; and quickly make our ſelues ready, that ſo we may ſet forth betimes towards the <hi>Celeſtiall Canaan.</hi> And when we haue once ſet our feete in the way of righteouſneſſe, the direct and only Rode to that Holy Citie, If at the end of our liues, when we can trauaile no longer, wee would reſt in <hi>Abrahams boſome:</hi> let vs labour to imitate him in his iourneying vnto the <hi>terreſtriall Canaan:</hi> that is, let vs <hi>eundo pergere,</hi> ſtill bee going forward <note place="margin">Gen. 129.</note> from grace to grace, whatſoeuer <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moraes</hi> doe encounter vs in the way, whatſoeuer afflictions doe befall vs
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:177608:67"/> hauing our eies fixt vpon thoſe heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioyes, whereof the troubles and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of this life are not worthy. The older we grow in yeares, the more let vs grow in goodneſſe: Let our Workes, our Loue, our Seruice, our Faith, our Patience be like the <hi>Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirians,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. 19.</note> more at the laſt then at the firſt. Thus like good Trees, bringing forth good fruit preſently, plentifully, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerantly; wee ſhall at length bee brought by him who is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 1. 8.</note> the <hi>beginning</hi> and the <hi>ending,</hi> vnto the <hi>beginning</hi> of that vnſpeakable Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe which ſhall haue <hi>no ending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But happily you will reply in the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note> who is ſufficient for theſe things? Is not our Father an <hi>Amorite,</hi> and our Mother a <hi>Hittite!</hi> The <hi>beſt</hi> of men by Nature is no better then a <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar,</hi> a <note place="margin">Micha 74. Math. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Thorne,</hi> a <hi>Thiſtle.</hi> And <hi>doe men gather Grapes of Thornes, and Figges of Thiſtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ex Spinis non naſcitur Roſa.</hi> Such as is the Tree, ſuch is the Fruite. Tis true: And therefore to bring forth Good fruit preſently, plentifully, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerantly, we muſt be <hi>ingrafted</hi> into the true <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine,</hi> and abide in it. <hi>I am that</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:177608:67"/> 
               <hi>Vine,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and yee are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 15. 5.</note> 
               <hi>He that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth</hi> good <hi>fruit: For without me ye can doe nothing. If a man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">verſe. 6.</note> 
               <hi>abide not in mee, hee is caſt forth as a branch that is withered, and men gather them, and caſt them into the fire, and they are burned.</hi> But how are we ingrafted into Chriſt? by Faith. How doe wee <hi>abide</hi> in Him? By Loue. How doth He abide in vs? by his Holy Spirit: through whoſe gracious opperation we are inabled to bring forth the good fruits of the Spirit: Now for aſmuch as no Arme of Fleſh can command this Faith, this Loue, this Holy Spirit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O LORD GOD, wee doe here in all humilitie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe our ſelues vnto thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie, entirely deſiring thee in mercy to looke downe from Heauen vpon vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wretches heere on earth. Wee acknowledge, O Lord,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:177608:68"/> and thou knoweſt, that of our ſelues wee haue no power to order our wayes aright vnto thee: for wee are a crooked generation, a people by nature the children of wrath: ſo that if thou ſhouldeſt leaue vs to our ſelues, we muſt looke for no leſſe, then like fruitleſſe Trees to bee hewen downe, and caſt into the fire. But, good God, remember that thou art our Creatour, and we thy Creatures: that thou art our Father, and wee thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Oh, neglect not the work of thine Hand; neither ſuffer vs thy children to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: but looke vpon vs in the ſweet compaſsions of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177608:68"/> hearted Father: for the blood of Chriſt pardon all our ſinnes paſt: throw behinde thy backe thoſe curſed fruits we haue hitherto continually brought foorth to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of thy Great and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name, that they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be layd vnto our charge: and enable vs for the time to come to doe what thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt, and then require what thou wilt, and we will doe it. O Lord ſtretch foorth thine hand, and engraft vs by a true and liuely Faith into the Body of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. Dwell in vs, O heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bleſſed Sonne by thy holy Spirit: that by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:177608:69"/> and powerfull operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, like good trees we may bring forth good fruit, that we may euery day more and more abound and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in grace and goodneſſe, till wee come to bee perfect men in Chriſt leſus. Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly heare vs, moſt mercifull Father, and graunt vs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou knoweſt to bee good for vs, and that for thy Sonne and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. To whome with thee and the bleſsed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, bee aſcribed of vs and of all thy Saints, all praiſe power and Glory for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177608:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
